<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The white wolfe, or, A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Feb. 11 being the last Sonday in Hillarie tearme, anno 1627, and printed somewhat more largely then the time would permit at that present to deliuer wherein faction is vnmasked, and iustly taxed without malice, for the safetie of weake Christians : especially, the Hetheringtonian faction growne very impudent in this citie of late yeeres, is here confuted / by Stephen Denison...</title>
            <author>Denison, Stephen, d. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6607.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23604063</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23604063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10126</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69197)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10126)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1063:13 or 1831:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The white wolfe, or, A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, Feb. 11 being the last Sonday in Hillarie tearme, anno 1627, and printed somewhat more largely then the time would permit at that present to deliuer wherein faction is vnmasked, and iustly taxed without malice, for the safetie of weake Christians : especially, the Hetheringtonian faction growne very impudent in this citie of late yeeres, is here confuted / by Stephen Denison...</title>
                  <author>Denison, Stephen, d. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 76 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller, dwelling in Blacke-Fryers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ [par.]² B-K⁴ L².</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 76.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 70-71 misnumbered 80-81.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and Union Theological Seminary Library (New York, N.Y.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Etherington, John, fl. 1641-1645.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VII, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Familists --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10126:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10126:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
WHITE WOLFE
<hi>OR,</hi>
A Sermon Preached at PAVLS
<hi>Croſſe, Feb.</hi> 11. <hi>being the laſt Sonday in Hillarie</hi>
Tearme, <hi>Anno</hi> 1627. and printed ſomewhat
<hi>more largely then the time would permit
at that preſent to deliuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein Faction is vnmasked, and iuſtly taxed
<hi>without malice, for the ſafetie of weake</hi>
CHRISTIANS.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, the <hi>Hetheringtonian</hi> Faction growne
very impudent in this Citie of late
yeeres, is here confuted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> STEPHEN DENISON, Miniſter of <hi>Katherine
Cree-Church, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. TIM. 1. 3.</bibl>
               <p>As I be ſought thee to abide ſtill at Epheſus, when I went into Macedonis, that
thou mighteſt charge ſome, that they teach no other Doctrine.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>HIER. aduerſ. LVCIFERIAN.</bibl>
               <p>Qu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>modo deſtructa ſunt Diaboli Ciuitates, &amp; in fine, hoc eſt in ſeculorum
conſummatione, idola corruerunt</p>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON,
Printed by GEORGE MILLER, dwelling in
Blacke-Fryers. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10126:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10126:2"/>
            <head>TO
THE HIGH
And Mighty PRINCE
CHARLES,
By the Grace of God, King of
Great Britaine, France, and Ireland, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of the FAITH, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Soueraigne, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eneca</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. de Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>nullum ex om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus
cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia magis quam
Regem aut principem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet;</hi>
Clemency becomes
no man better then a
King or Prince, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
fully perſwaded, that this, together with
all other both Princely and ſauing graces
meete in your Maieſties royall breaſt, euen
as the lines of a circumference meete in the
<pb facs="tcp:10126:3"/>
center or middle point: I am encouraged to
preſent this Sermon to your Princely view.
I know indeed it is not with Kings as<note n="*" place="margin">Eidyl. 15. v. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus</hi>
ſaith, it is with perſons without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which keepe euery
day holy day: the imployments and labours
of Princes are farre greater then ordinary
Subiects can conceiue: yet I hope I may ſay
of your Maieſty, as<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 1 c. 1. ad Thraſimund re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem.</note> 
               <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith of <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimund</hi>
the King vnto whom he writes, <hi>te nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroſis
Regni curis iugiter occupatum, feruenti
cognoſcendae ſapientiae dilectatione flammari;</hi> that
howſoeuer your royall heart be much taken
vp with manifold cares co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
for the common ſafety of all your
Subiects, yet it is inflamed alſo with a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
zeale after the beſt things; your Maieſty
is a Defender of the true Chriſtian Faith, in
which reſpect you are highly honoured and
ſincerely beloued of all your true hearted
and truely Religious Subiects: no doubt
they dayly pray for you, they bleſſe God for
you, they eſteeme you the breath of their
noſtrills, and this loue of the Subiects is to
be eſteemed by Kings their ſtrongeſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
or Caſtell in reſpect of ordinarie
<pb facs="tcp:10126:3"/>
meanes; as<note n="*" place="margin">In Orat. ad Nicocl. de regno.</note> 
               <hi>Iſocrates</hi> ſaith to <hi>Nicocles</hi> the
King, in his Greeke Oration made before
him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:
i. e. <hi>thinke the loue of the Citizens
the ſafeſt guard of thy perſon:</hi> &amp; indeede ſo it
is vnder God. There hath bin diſcouered of
late vnto your Maieſties high Commiſſion-Court,
a dangerous familiſticall ſectarie, one
<hi>Iohn Hetherington,</hi> by trade a Boxmaker,
who hath ſeduced and withdrawne many as
well men as women from the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> in the famous Citie of <hi>London,</hi> by
his ſubtile ſuggeſtions, as hath bin proued
againſt him. I cannot more fitly deſcribe
him then by the words of my Text; <hi>Lupus
eſt ouili pelle tectus:</hi> hee is a Woolfe in a
Sheepes-skinne: for outwardly if he liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
Proteſtants, hee will ſeeme to be a
Proteſtant, if a bare profeſſion <hi>ore tenus,</hi> will
ſerue the turne, whilſt in the meane time hee
may gird at them in his writings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
them as adulterous Congregations
in his Conuenticles or otherwiſe. Secondly,
hee will ſeeme to be a conformable man to
the Doctrine of the Church, if ſubtile equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations
and cunning euaſions will paſſe
<pb facs="tcp:10126:4"/>
for conformitie. Thirdly, hee will ſeeme an
innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſon, if impudent denials or caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of aſperſions vpon honeſt witneſſes will
goe for innocency. And in this, that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
quickſighted and Eagle-eyed Court
deſerueth great encouragement; in that,
when they had to deale with one that would
deny almoſt all that was laid to his charge,
yet they diſcerned aright of him, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
cenſured him; and thus the Greeke
Prouerbe is verified <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The
Woolfe thinkes to run from the Eagle, and
ſo to eſcape, but all in vaine: and amongſt
thoſe worthy and learned Commiſſioners,
he that is the chiefe, <hi>optimo iure primas agit:</hi>
whoſe <hi>acumen,</hi> whoſe ſoundneſſe in the faith,
whoſe ſingular grauity, whoſe happy ſpeech,
whoſe excellent parts euery way are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
grace of that venerable Court: it may be
ſaid of him as<note n="*" place="margin">Orat. 30. in laudem Baſil.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> ſaith of
S. <hi>Baſil</hi> Archbiſhop of Caeſarea (whom he
ſtiles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that <hi>he is like vnto No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,
vnto whom the Arke of the Church is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted,
and ſo kept from drowning, whiles it floats
in the turbulent waters amongſt Haereticks.</hi> And
whiles I am ſpeaking of Eccleſiaſticall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies,
<pb facs="tcp:10126:4"/>
very dutie will not ſuffer me to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull
of him, vnder whom the Miniſters
of <hi>London</hi> liue as children vnder the care of
an indulgent Father: his great humility will
not ſuffer him to Lord it ouer the Clergie,
nor his peaceable diſpoſition to yrannize:
it may be ſaid of him as<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 4. epiſt. 9</note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop
of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſaith of himſelfe in one of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles;
<hi>Humilitatem meam &amp; fratres omnes &amp;
gentiles norunt &amp; diligunt.</hi> I finde that I haue
ſtirred vp to wrath againſt my ſelfe the moſt
part of all the factions in <hi>England</hi> by this
publike Sermon, which I made in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of Gods eternall truth, in loue to my
Country, and in compaſſion of weake bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
which are in the moſt danger of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.
I remember Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that he
had fought with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> after the
manner of men, and in like ſort it befalleth
vnto mee at this time: I haue to deale with
young Foxes which ſpoyle the Vine of the
Church, and with Wolues, which ſeeke to
ſtrangle the Sheep of Chriſt: but what then?
ſo long as I ſtand for that truth, whereof
your excellent Maieſtie is a defender, I doe
not doubt of acceptation, and if my poore
<pb facs="tcp:10126:5"/>
endeauours ſhall be ſo happy as to finde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation
with your ſacred perſon as they
haue found in the learned Court before
your Maieſties Commiſſioners, and in the
audience where the Sermon was preached,
euen this acceptation greater then all the
reſt, ſhall be all-ſufficient to blunt the edge
of all the power of the aduerſary, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
the Author from wrong and violence;
yea, it ſhall no doubt encourage many able
men in the Kingdome to take paines in the
ſuppreſſing of faction, both by preaching
and writing, ſo farre as ſhall be thought fit by
authoritie. Thus crauing pardon for my
boldneſſe, I beſeech almighty God to bleſſe
your Maieſty with long life, &amp; many happy
dayes, with abundance of all gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
in this world, and with eternall glory in
that which is to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt
humble ſubiect,
<hi>STEPHEN DENISON,
Miniſter of</hi> Cree-Church, London.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10126:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou which haſt a tender conſcience, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
nothing ſo much as to know the right way
to heauen, hauing alſo many doubts, which
cauſe thee to runne vp and downe, ſometimes
to the publike Congregations, and other
ſometimes to priuate Conuenticles, for reſolution. I haue for
thy ſake and ſafety vndertaken this paines; whereby I haue
incenſed many factious perſons againſt my ſelfe, expoſed my
good name to the obloquie of a thouſand bad tongues, and
made ſomewhat to bold with my owne Flocke whilst I was
painefully imployed in this more laborious worke, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
a more generall and publike good I haue had no helpe
in this ſeruice, ſaue onely the good Aſſiſtance of Authority,
for the which I hope I ſhall praiſe God as long as I liue, and
the teſtimonies of honeſt witneſſes. For howſoeuer there were
many which diſliked the Hetheringtonian Faction, abhorred
their opinions, complained of them to Ministers in ſecret,
and murmured againſt them which ſhould ſee theſe things
reformed, yet for any that would lend their helping hand to
ſet forward this matter of ſo great importance for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
ſafety of the Church: I found none, vnleſſe it were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the Latine Prouerbe <hi>poſt bellum ſuppetiae.</hi> I met
alſo with many diſcouragements, ſome in their ignorance
would be ready to ſay, that though this faction held ſome ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd
points, yet that they held nothing againſt the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
not vnderſtanding how they vndermine Religion at the
very roote of it: for grant vnto them this, that our Church
is no true Church of Christ, that our Miniſters are no true
Miniſters of the Goſpell, that our beſt Profeſſors are Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10126:6"/>
               <figure>
                  <p>The WOOLFE in a
Sheepes Skinne.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10126:6"/>
            <head>BVT BEVVARE
OF FALSE
PROPHETS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <bibl>MAT. 7. 15.</bibl>
               <q>But beware yee of falſe Prophets which come vnto you
in Sheepes cloathings, but inwardly they are rauening
Wolues.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter and the two former wee
haue that famous and learned Sermon of
our Sauiour, made by him in the Mount,
graphically penned and ſet downe by our
holy Euangeliſt Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> one of
the bleſſed pen-men of ſacred Scripture,
and ſecretary to the holy Ghoſt. In the deſcription of
which Sermon we haue three maine parts; the Preface,
the Narration, and the Concluſion: the Preface in the firſt
and ſecond Verſes of the fift Chapter, wherein are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
diuers neceſſary circumſtances belonging to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:
as firſt, the Author of it <hi>hee. i. e.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10126:7"/>
the place, <hi>a Mountaine.</hi> Thirdly, the geſture vſed
by our Sauiour, <hi>fitting downe.</hi> Fourthly, the perſons whom
he taught <hi>his Diſciples.</hi> Fiftly, the manner of expreſſion,
<hi>when he had opened his mouth.</hi> The narration begins at the
third verſe of the fift Chapter, and endeth in the 23. verſe
of the ſeauenth Chapter, and it is partly conſolatory from
the third verſe to the end of the 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and therein our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
demonſtrateth the procreant cauſes of true happineſſe
for the comfort of weake Chriſtians. Partly exhortatory
from the 13. verſe to the end of the 16. and therein he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth
his Diſciples to walke worthy of their moſt holy
calling. Partly interpretatory from the 17. verſe to the end
of the fifth Chapter: and therein hee vindicates diuers of
the Commandements from the falſe gloſſes of the Scribes
and Phariſees. Partly dehortatory in all the ſixt Chapter
and beginning of the ſeauen. In the ſixt hee dehorteth his
Diſciples fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two Phariſaicall ſinnes, <hi>viz.</hi> vaine-glory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
almes deeds, faſting &amp; prayer from the firſt verſe
to the end of the 18. and couetouſneſſe expreſſed by world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
cares from verſe the 19. to the end of the Chapter. This
Dehortatory part is alſo continued in the beginning of the
ſeauenth Chapter from the firſt verſe to the ſixt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
he dehorteth from two ſinnes more, to wit, raſh iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
verſ. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. and raſh communicating of holy
things to vnworthy perſons, verſ. 6. partly excitatory to
the dutie of prayer, verſ. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. partly declaratory
demonſtrating the maine thing, the Law and the Prophets
aime at in their doctrine. Partly directory concerning the
way to heauen, verſ. 13, 14. and partly premonitory, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
warning concerning falſe Prophets, and other things
depending thereupon, from verſ. 15. to the end of the 23.
Then in the laſt place wee haue the Epilogue or Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
from the 24. verſe to the end of the ſeauenth Chapter,
wherein we haue Chriſt his application of his whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
ver. 24, 25, 26, 27. expreſſed by an elegant compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
taken from builders, and the effect which followed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
this excellent pithie Sermon in the hearts of the hearers,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10126:7"/>
which was aſtoniſhment or admiration in the two laſt
verſes.</p>
               <p>By the which Logicall Analyſis we may conceiue, that
this Text is a maine part of the narration or ſubiect matter
of the Sermon it ſelfe, being the very premonicion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
falſe Prophets, and alſo vpon what occaſion it is
brought in, namely immediately vpon a direction giuen
concerning the ſtrait way to heauen in the two verſes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
before: and it is as if our Sauiour had ſaid, I know my
deare Diſciples that you hearing of the narrow way
which leadeth to happineſſe, will be deſirous after the
manner of trauellers to aske all that you meet but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
thoſe which ſeeme to be Prophets, concerning this
way for your better confirmation and conduction. But let
me forewarne you of all other to beware how you aske di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
of falſe guides: for they inſtead of directing you,
will ſet you quite out of the way, as it is the<note n="c" place="margin">Haereſis enim rectè gradientes ab itinere ſuo deuiare &amp; ad ſe diuertere docet. Hier. in 9. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb.</note> manner of
Hereſie ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>In the Text it ſelfe wee haue two parts: Firſt, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours
caueat giuen to his Church concerning Seducers, in
theſe words; <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets.</hi> Secondly, his
liuely deſcription of them, in the reſt of the Text. In the
firſt we haue two things; a title, <hi>Falſe Prophets;</hi> and a
caution, <hi>beware yee.</hi> In the ſecond our Sauiour giues a
double deſcription of ſeducers: and firſt hee deſcribeth
them by their outward habit, or externall ſhew; <hi>they come
vnto you in Sheepes cloathing.</hi> Secondly, by their internall
qualitie or diſpoſition, <hi>but inwardly they are rauening
Wolues.</hi> In the handling of this Text we will obſerue this
method. Firſt, we will ſpeake of the intent, or of the Text
in generall. Secondly, of the extent, or of the particular
application thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:10126:8"/>
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Of falſe Prophets.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FAlſe Prophets.</hi>] Hauing diſpatched the Logicall Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis,
and diuided the Text into its ſeuerall branches,
in the former Section: come we now (<hi>Christo duce</hi>) to
the particulars as they haue bin placed in the Diuiſion.
And firſt of the firſt: namely the title, <hi>falſe Prophets.</hi> The
word Prophet is vſed in two ſenſes in the Scripture; in a
ſtrict ſenſe, and in a large: in a ſtrict, and thus it is put for
a prenunciator or foreteller of things to come, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
from the Greeke verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifieth to
diuine: and of theſe diuiners there haue bin two ſorts:
firſt, ſuch as did diuine truely and ſincerely, thus <hi>Agabus</hi>
was a true Prophet, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. 28. foretelling of a famine,
which alſo came to paſſe in the dayes of <hi>Claudius Caeſar.</hi>
Secondly, ſuch as did diuine falſely, or if truely, yet not
ſincerely: ſuch as did diuine falſely, thus thoſe 400. in
1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. which propheſied that <hi>Ahab</hi> might goe vp to
<hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi> and proſper, were falſe Prophets, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
by the euent. And thus the heathen Oracles, which
propheſied (as<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 18. de Ciuit. Dei. c. 54.</note> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> hath it) that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
Religion ſhould continue but 365. yeares, were found
lying Oracles, our Religion hauing continued already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
ſixteene hundred yeeres. Secondly, ſuch as did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciate
truely but not ſincerely: thus the<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. Sibyllin Orac.</note> nine <hi>Sibyls</hi>
which ſprung vp amongſt the Heathen, and propheſied
concerning the incarnation of Chriſt, and of his comming
to iudgement, they were not to be eſteemed true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſſes,
becauſe howſoeuer they predicted many truths,
yet they ſerued the diuels turne in that which they did:
ſeeking the credit of his kingdome, and not the glory of
God. Much like vnto our vnwitching witches, which doe
ſome ſeeming good in the Common-wealth in helping
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10126:8"/>
men ſometimes to their goods, and yet cannot be truely
called good members, becauſe what good they doe they
doe in the diuels name, for the crediting of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;
doing a thouſand times more miſchiefe to mens
ſoules that ſeeke vnto them, then good to their bodies or
eſtates.</p>
               <p>Now here a queſtion may be moued, <hi>viz.</hi> whether the
gift of true ſincere prediction in matters diuine be vtterly
ceaſed or no. Learned<note n="a" place="margin">In Problem Loc. de Prophet temerarium eſt negare in totum Eccleſiae etiam hodiernae hoc do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Propheticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>Aretius</hi> ſaith, that it were raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
totally to denie the gift of Propheſie to the whole
Church at theſe dayes; but with the peace of that learned
and worthy man, I will be bold to ſay that the <hi>donum Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticum,</hi>
or gift of Propheſying, as it was in the Prophets
of old, which did breath new Scripture, and foretell things
to come certainely and infallibly, is finally ceaſed, becauſe
the Scripture is now ſo compleat, as that nothing muſt be
added thereunto, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 22. 18.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the word Prophet is taken ſometimes in a
large ſence, and thus it is vſed for a chiefe Speaker or
Teacher: and in this ſence Miniſters are called Prophets
in diuers places of the new Teſtament: and thus alſo the
Heathen Prieſts which were<note n="c" place="margin">Feſtus apud Stephan. in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauro Graeca Linguae.</note> 
                  <hi>Antistites fanorum,</hi> as one
ſpeaketh, the Clarkes of the Cloſſet in the Idols Temples,
were called Prophets. Thus in like manner <hi>Aratus</hi> and
<hi>Epimenides</hi> Heathen Poets are tearmed Prophets in holy
Scripture as being chiefe ſpeakers and teachers amongſt
their Countrimen. Thus the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is the
vſuall word in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Bible, put for a Prophet, comes
of the root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as two of the Iewiſh<note n="e" place="margin">Rab. Shelom.</note> Rabbines which are
beſt Interpreters of the propriety of their owne language
haue noted,<note n="e" place="margin">Aben Eſra in c. 7. Exod. ver. 1.</note> and the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies to ſpeake
as well as to bud. And herein appeareth the vſefulneſſe of
the Iewiſh Doctors, in that they goe beyond all the Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons
in the world for the naturall deriuation of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
words of the old Teſtament from the right roots in
the right ſenſe: indeede they are mad Interpreters of the
matter of Scripture, therein God hath iuſtly caſt vpon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10126:9"/>
them the ſpirit of ſlumber, but they are acute Interpreters
of the words.</p>
               <p>Here in my Text the word Prophet is taken in the large
ſence <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, falſe Prophets being put for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
falſe Teachers, by a <hi>Synecdoche ſpeciei magis
exquiſitae,</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">Alfledius in rhetor.</note> Rhetoricians ſpeak; a more particular tearme
being vſed for a more generall. For it is not ment of ſuch
Mountebankes, as tooke vpon them to foretell things to
come, which commonly are the obiects of ſcorne and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion,
that we ſhould beware of them. Although it is
true we muſt take heed of harkning vnto ſuch; but rather
of ſuch impoſtors and ſeducers as tooke vpon them to be
chiefe ſpeakers amongſt others, pretending either to ſpeak
immediately from God by reuelation, as deified or rather
diabolized familiſts, or illuminated or rather occaecated
anabaptiſts and other enthuſiaſts make their deluded pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites
beleeue they doe, or elſe to ſpeake from the Oracle
of Gods word by an eſpecial inſight as they ſuppoſe, giuen
vnto them to interpret Gods meaning in ſacred writ, as
the Pope pretendeth he hath.</p>
               <p>And leſt that any ſhould erroniouſly iudge that by falſe
Prophets here are meant onely erronious Miniſters, and
ſuch as are in orders, wee are to know that the word
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is according to the proper ſignification as
much as <hi>falſo Prophetae;</hi> that is, ſuch as properly are not
prophets, but onely pretend themſelues to be ſo: and in
this reſpect falſe guides amongſt the people are as well
meant here by pſeudoprophets, as amongſt the Miniſters.
Thus much for the title giuen by our Sauiour to decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
of mindes, and that by way of expoſition; as for
the Vſe and application, it followes in the next Section
ſaue one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10126:9"/>
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Beware of falſe Prophets.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beware yee:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifies
properly <hi>adhibete,</hi> apply yee; as though hee had ſaid
apply your minde or heart. This word is taken in two ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:
Firſt, in the ſenſe of attending in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<hi>Wee haue a more ſure word of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
to the which yee doe well that you doe attend.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
in the ſenſe of bewaring in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<hi>Beware leaſt you giue your almes to be ſeene of
men.</hi> In which ſenſe alſo the Heathen man vſeth it,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Epictet in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chir. c. 36.</note> take
heede leaſt thou be as little children, which ſometime af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
to be a Philoſopher, ſometimes to be a Publicane,
ſometimes to be a Rhetoritian, and ſometimes to be <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi>
Tutor. In my Text the word is taken in the latter
ſence, namely for bewaring, as you haue it faithfully tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated
in our laſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlation; vnto which alſo the
<hi>Syrian</hi> tranſlation agrees <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which in the forme
ithpehal ſignifies, be ye forewarned; and the <hi>Arabicke</hi>
in like manner <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ocdſhorou,</hi> which in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iugation
in the imperatiue mood ſignifies <hi>Cauete,</hi> beware
yee, or take ye heed. Thus for the meaning of the word
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets.</hi> Our Sauiour giues this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat
both to his Diſciples preſent, and alſo to all ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Chriſtian Churches, to the end of the world. To his
Diſciples preſent, becauſe in their very<note n="c" place="margin">Teſte Ioſepho lib. 18. c. 2. anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit.</note> dayes the Church
was annoyed with diuers pernicious Sects: with the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,
which like vnto our Papiſts, held Iuſtification by
humane merits: with the Saduces, which held like vnto
our Atheiſts, that the ſoule periſheth with the body: with
the Eſſens, which thought themſelues to be free from all
humane authority: like vnto our Anabaptiſts, whom I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10126:10"/>
tearme ours, not becauſe they are of vs, but becauſe like
vnwelcome gueſts, they will needes liue amongſt vs: for
this cauſe Chriſt forewarneth his Diſciples here to beware
of falſe Prophets, that is, to beware of the Phariſees, leſt
their iudgement ſhould be corrupted in the maine, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
concerning the Doctrin of Iuſtification. Secondly, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
of the Saduces, leſt by their Atheiſme they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
ſhould be weakned in their faith. Thirdly, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
of the Eſſens, leſt by their example they ſhould ſhake
of the yoake of ſubiection. And in this our bleſſed Sauiour
ſhould be a patterne to all the Miniſters of the Goſpell,
to teach them to the vttermoſt of their power to endeauor
to beat downe the Errors that either ſpring vp, or elſe are
moſt riſe in their times. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3,</p>
               <p>Secondly, this caueat is alſo giuen by our Sauiour to all
ſucceeding Churches, becauſe he foreſaw by the ſpirit of
Propheſie, that many falſe Prophets would ariſe in after
times, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 24. he foreſaw Antichriſt ariſing in the
Weſt in the <hi>Romane</hi> Chaire, from the dayes of <hi>Boniface</hi>
the third, who ambitiouſly obtained of<note n="c" place="margin">Teſte Platina in vita eiuſdem Bonifacij.</note> 
                  <hi>Phocas</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
to be called the Aecumenicall or Vniuerſall Biſhop
of the whole Chriſtian world; and therein approued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
to be <hi>praecurſorem Antichristi</hi> (as<note n="c" place="margin">In Epiſt. lib. 4. Epiſt. 76.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt
ſpeaks) the very forerunner of Antichriſt; and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
all the Popes that euer haue ſucceeded him in that
ſea, to haue bin <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that great Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he foreſaw many falſe Prophets ariſing in the
virgin-time of the Church, in the firſt 500. yeares after his
aſcenſion, and therefore forewarneth his Church which
were to liue in thoſe ages, to beware of falſe Prophets, as
he fore warneth vs and all Churches that haue liued before
vs for the ſpace of a thouſand yeares and vpwards in the
times of Antichriſt, or that euer ſhall liue hereafter to the
end of the world, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
of the Pope, and his Antichriſtian Doctrine. And
this muſt teach weake Chriſtians not to take ſcandall,
though there be many ſtrangly affected in religion at theſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10126:10"/>
dayes. Chriſt told vs before-hand that falſe Prophets
would ariſe, and wiſhed vs to beware of them, but not
to be offended or to take offence at the truth becauſe of
them. And to the end we may not thinke it ſtrange to ſee
ſo many Sects and Schiſmes in our dayes, I thinke it not
impertinent to name the ſeuerall ſorts of Sectaries and
Haeretickes which haue ſprung vp in the moſt pure ages of
the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> in the firſt 500. yeares after Chriſt.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>A Catalogue of Sectaries and Haeretickes
which ſprang vp in the Primitiue Church
collected by Saint Auguſtine Lib. de
Haereſibus, out of Euſebius
and Epiphanius.</head>
                  <item>1 SImoniani.</item>
                  <item>2 Menandriani.</item>
                  <item>3 Saturniniani.</item>
                  <item>4 Baſilidiani.</item>
                  <item>5 Nicolaitae.</item>
                  <item>6 Gnoſtici.</item>
                  <item>7 Carpocratiani.</item>
                  <item>8 Cerinthiani.</item>
                  <item>9 Nazaraes.</item>
                  <item>10 Hebiones.</item>
                  <item>11 Valentiniani.</item>
                  <item>12 Secundiani.</item>
                  <item>13 Ptolemai.</item>
                  <item>14 Marcitae.</item>
                  <item>15 Colarbaſij.</item>
                  <item>16 Heracleonitae.</item>
                  <item>17 Orphitae.</item>
                  <item>18 Caini.</item>
                  <item>19 Sethani.</item>
                  <item>20 Archontici.</item>
                  <item>21 Cerdoniani.</item>
                  <item>22 Macionitae.</item>
                  <item>23 Apellitae.</item>
                  <item>24 Seuereani.</item>
                  <item>25 Taciani.</item>
                  <item>26 Cataphryges.</item>
                  <item>27 Peputiani.</item>
                  <item>28 Artotyritae.</item>
                  <item>29 Teſſareſcaedecatitae.</item>
                  <item>30 Alogiani.</item>
                  <item>31 Adamiani.</item>
                  <item>32 Elceſcitae.</item>
                  <item>33 Theodotiani.</item>
                  <item>34 Melcheſidechitae.</item>
                  <item>35 Bardeſanita.</item>
                  <item>36 Noetiani.</item>
                  <item>37 Valeſij.</item>
                  <item>38 Cathari.</item>
                  <item>39 Angelici.</item>
                  <item>40 Apoſtolici.</item>
                  <item>41 Sabelliani.</item>
                  <item>42 Oregeniani.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:10126:11"/>
43 Originiastae.</item>
                  <item>44 Paul<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>jta.</item>
                  <item>45 Ph<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiniani.</item>
                  <item>46 Manichaei.</item>
                  <item>47 Hierachitae.</item>
                  <item>48 Melitiani.</item>
                  <item>49 Ariani.</item>
                  <item>50 Vadiani.</item>
                  <item>51 Semiariani.</item>
                  <item>52 Macedoniani.</item>
                  <item>53 Aeriani.</item>
                  <item>54 Pauliani.</item>
                  <item>55 Apollinariſtae.</item>
                  <item>56 Antidicomarianitae.</item>
                  <item>57 Pſalliani.</item>
                  <item>58 Metangiſmonitae.</item>
                  <item>59 Seluciani.</item>
                  <item>60 Proclianitae.</item>
                  <item>61 Patriciani.</item>
                  <item>62 Aſcitae.</item>
                  <item>63 Patralorinchitae.</item>
                  <item>64 Aquarij.</item>
                  <item>65 Caluthiani.</item>
                  <item>66 Florimiani.</item>
                  <item>67 De mundi. ſtatu diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientes.</item>
                  <item>68 Nudis pedibus ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes.</item>
                  <item>69 Donatistae.</item>
                  <item>70 Priſcilliani.</item>
                  <item>71 Cum her<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inibus non
manducantes.</item>
                  <item>72 Rhetorani.</item>
                  <item>73 Christi diuinitatem paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilem
dicentes.</item>
                  <item>74 Triformem deum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes.</item>
                  <item>75 Aquam deo Coaeternam
tenentes.</item>
                  <item>76 Corpus hominis non ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam
eſſe imaginem dei
aſſerentes.</item>
                  <item>77 Innumerabiles mundos
opinantes.</item>
                  <item>78 Animas conuerti in dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones
tenentes.</item>
                  <item>79 Omnes liberatos fuiſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud
inferos Chriſti di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſu
putantes.</item>
                  <item>80 Chriſti de patre natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati
initium a tempore
dantes.</item>
                  <item>81 Leciferiani.</item>
                  <item>82 Iouinianistae.</item>
                  <item>83 Arabici.</item>
                  <item>84 Heluidiani.</item>
                  <item>85 Paterniani.</item>
                  <item>86 Tertullianiſtae.</item>
                  <item>87 Abeloitae.</item>
                  <item>88 <hi>Pelagiani.</hi> vnto which
may be added <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani,
&amp; Euticiani.</hi> What
all theſe Haeretiks held
the learned may read
<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de hareſ. Tom. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>ibidem.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe I ſay ſprang vp in the more pure times of the
Church, and therefore it is no maruell if there be ſo many
Schiſmatikes and Sectaries in our times. Neither let Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10126:11"/>
or others reproach the Church, or ſay it is no Church,
becauſe many ſects are in it: for as a Cornefield reteines
the name of a Cornefield, though it haue many blew-bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles
and other ſtinking weedes growing vp amongſt the
Corne; euen ſo the Church is a Church, although many
Schiſmatikes like ſo many tares are ſowne in it by the
meanes of the enuious man of hell. And indeede the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
haue little reaſon of all other to obiect againſt vs the
multitude of ſectaries, conſidering how faction abounds
and ſuperabounds amongſt themſelues. Haue they not
the Thomiſts againſt the Scotiſts, and the Scotiſts againſt
the Thomiſts, and the Occhamiſts againſt them both? haue
they not the Ieſuites againſt the Friers, and the Friers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Ieſuites, and the Maſſe-prieſts enuying
both? yea, what are their ſeuerall orders of Franciſcanes,
Dominicans, Auguſtinians, and ſuch like, but ſo many
different factions amongſt themſelues diſagreeing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes they be tyed together by
the tayles with fire-brands betweene, being ouer-aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by the Pope the Arch-ſectarie, and the Inquiſition-tortures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Beware of falſe Prophets.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beware: where obſerue, Firſt, that it is not
ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ſingular number, as though our
Sauiour had ſpoken onely to ſome one man, that hee
ſhould beware of falſe Prophets. Secondly, that it is not
ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the duall number, as though he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
to ſome two in the world; but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
number, to intimate that he ſpake vnto all that euer
ſhould take vpon them the title of Chriſtians to the end of
the world.</p>
               <p>And indeede it is the dutie of all Chriſtians, of what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10126:12"/>
ranke ſoeuer they be, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to
beware of falſe Prophets.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Kings and Princes muſt beware of them, and that
both in reſpect of themſelues, and alſo in reſpect of their
ſubiects. In reſpect of themſelues, they muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
looke to themſelues, leſt any ſonne of <hi>Belial,</hi> or any
inſtrument of Antichriſt be ſo impudent as to preſſe into
their roiall preſence to ſeduce them, and this they had
neede to looke vnto with infinite circumſpection; becauſe
the beloued Diſciple Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Apocalips, c. 16. v.
13, 14. giues them an <hi>item,</hi> that three vncleane ſpirits like
frogs ſhall come out of the mouth of the Dragon, and out
of the mouth of the falſe Prophet, being ſpirits of Diuels
working miracles, and going forth to the Kings of the
earth, and of the whole world, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Princes muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware
of falſe Prophets in reſpect of their ſubiects. They
muſt take the Foxes, the yong Foxes which ſpoile the
Vines, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. 15. they muſt not giue any toleration to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry
in the Lords Land; but like good <hi>Ioſias,</hi> in their
time they muſt take away all the abominations, and cauſe
all men to ſerue the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 33. Princes are
Shepheards of the people, ſo the Euangelicall Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi>
ſtileth them in his 44. Chapter verſe 28. that ſaith of
<hi>Cyrus, hee is my Shepheard, &amp;c.</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Dryantem etiam paſtorem populi.</note> 
                  <hi>Homer</hi> the King of
Poets giues them the like title, in the firſt of his <hi>Iliads</hi> tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<hi>Dryas</hi> a Shepheard, who was indeede the Prince or
C<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ef-taine of the people. Now as it is the care of Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rds
not to ſuffer noyſome Beaſts, Wolues, and the like,
<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue their dens amongſt their Sheepe: euen ſo it ought
to be the care of all Chriſtian Princes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>abigere Lupos,</hi>
not to ſuffer Idolaters to ſet vp their abhominations in
any part of their Kingdome: the danger that may in any
ſort accrue vnto Princes (whoſe ſoules doe thou O Lord
alwayes binde vp in the bundle of life) comes not by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying
vnto Idolaters that which tends to their owne hurt,
no more then euill vnto indulgent Parents by denying
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10126:12"/>
kniues and poyſon to their Children, when they earneſtly
cry for ſuch things, but the danger is rather in ſatisfying
their vnlawfull and ſinfull deſires, for herein they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke
Gods anger againſt themſelues, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11. 9. <hi>Reuel.</hi>
2. 20.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Miniſters muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
beware of falſe Prophets. They muſt beware of reading
and preferring the erronious poſtils of pſeudoprophets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the Orthodox writings of ſound Diuines: the want of
this good take heed is the cauſe that many young Miniſters
come quickly to be corrupted in their iudgements, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
of teaching, doe rather corrupt others. Secondly, they
muſt beware in reſpect of their flocke (<hi>caueant Ministri</hi>)
leſt while they ſleepe the enuibus man ſowe tares, as it is in
the Goſpell.<note n="c" place="margin">Mala eſt pax<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; concordia quae inter paſtores &amp; Lupos eſt, Che<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius in harmon. Euangel.</note> Thirdly, they muſt beware of entertaining
peace with common ſeducers, that is an euill peace and a
bad concord indeede which is betweene the Shepheards
and the Wolues, as a learned man ſpeaketh. Thirdly, they
(and I doe not exclude my ſelfe) muſt beware of being
conuerſant, or familiar; or delighting in the company of
the enemies of Gods truth, and of his ſeruants: it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
by <hi>Euſebius</hi> concerning <hi>Iohn</hi> the beloued Diſciple of
Chriſt, that when <hi>Cerinthus</hi> that damnable haeretick came
into the ſame Bath where <hi>Iohn</hi> was waſhing himſelfe, the
Apoſtle ſprang or leapt out of the Bath, as the Author
<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: Euſeb. lib. 4. Eccleſ. hiſt. c. 14.</note> ſignificantly ſpeaketh, fearing leſt God ſhould haue
ſhowne a viſible iudgement vpon him by the fall of the
roofe of the Bath, if he had remained in the company of
ſuch a wretch. Oh that there were ſuch an abhorring in
vs Miniſters at theſe dayes, for ſurely then errours would
not ſo thriue as they doe. Fourthly, Miniſters, muſt take
diligent notice of the errours that ſpring vp in their times,
as the learned Fathers did in their dayes, and by their
preaching muſt beat downe to their power the ſame er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors.
It is reported concerning the Mother of <hi>Gregorie
Nazi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nzene,</hi> by ſome (although it be ſomewhat other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
recorded by others in the life of the ſame reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10126:13"/>
That ſhe dreamed when ſhee was conceiued of that
worthy light of the Church, that ſhee had in her wombe
a white whelpe which by his barking ſhould driue away
the Wolues from the Sheepefold. I ſtand not vpon the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie,
but I wiſh that all the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> were
ſuch white whelpes as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> was, and that
their preaching were like vnto his barking to feare away
the wolues from the ſheepfold of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the people muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
beware of falſe Prophets. For firſt they muſt beware of
hearing them, either publikely if at any time they intrude
themſelues, or priuately in their clandeſtine or ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles.
The Sheepe of Chriſt will not heare the voice
of a ſtranger, but flye from him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 5. It is recorded
by <hi>Theodorite,</hi> that when <hi>Lucius</hi> an arian Biſhop came and
preached amongſt the Antiochians broaching his damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
errors, the people<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. 4. Eccleſ. hiſt. c. 20. in hiſt. trip.</note> forſooke the Congregations at the
leaſt for the preſent, hauing indeede bin ſoundly taught
before by worthy <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Oh that the people of this
age had their witts thus exerciſed to iudge betwixt truth
and falſehood: but alas at theſe dayes, if error come but
masked with a pretence of zeale &amp; a thundering voice, it is
readily receiued for truth by the common multitude, yea I
would there were not many that make a great profeſſion
of religion, and yet are thus ſilly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beware: in that our Sauiour onely mentions
here a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a dutie of bewaring of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
<hi>ergo,</hi> it may fitly be demanded and that as a caſe of
conſcience, whether it be lawfull for the Church <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
to put falſe Prophets to death. In
the which queſtion we muſt carefully note whom wee are
to vnderſtand by falſe Prophets. And by falſe Prophets
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10126:13"/>
in this queſtion concerning life and death, wee are not to
vnderſtand them that differ in opinion from vs in ſmaller
matters, although I wiſh from my heart that we were all
of one iudgement in the leaſt things, as well as in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt:
neither are we to vnderſtand thereby them which of
meere ſimple ignorance hold ſome error at the leaſt for a
time againſt the maine foundation of Chriſtian religion.
The Apoſtles themſelues were ignorant for a time, both
of the death, and alſo of the reſurrection of Chriſt, and
therefore when our Sauiour ſpake of either of theſe, they
wondered, as being carried away indeede (as men, though
not as Apoſtles) with the common error of the times,
which was this, to wit, that the Meſſiah ſhould neuer dye,
and ſo by conſequence ſhould neuer riſe againe. But by
falſe Prophets in this queſtion we are to vnderſtand, firſt
ſuch as obſtinately perſiſt in fundamentall errors, after ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
meanes vſed for their conuiction, yea not onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
but alſo endeauour to diſperſe their pernicious errors
to the peruerting of others, ſeeking withall to ſupplant
and to blaſpheme the contrary truth: according to that
deſcription of falſe Prophets giuen by a learned<note n="e" place="margin">Pſeudoprophetae ſunt qui docent contra veritatem fidei. Toſtat. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bul. ad loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Spaniard;</hi>
they are falſe Prophets which teach againſt the truth of the
faith, Secondly, ſuch alſo, whoſe Haereſies are either Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
in the doctrine it ſelfe, as the Arians; or traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
againſt Soueraigntie, as the Ieſuites: and where both
theſe concurre, the perſons in whom they meet do certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
deſerue a thouſand deaths. Firſt, becauſe they corrupt the
faith, and if ſuch as corrupt and poiſon the ſprings of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
at the which men and beaſts receiue their drinke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
capitall puniſhment, how much more they, which
as much as in them is, doe impoiſon the freſh ſprings of
Sion. Secondly, becauſe they murder mens ſoules, yea as
farre as poſſibly they can, they murder Chriſt in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
man,<note place="margin">Quantum in ipſis eſt Chriſtum in homini occidunt.</note> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes in his fift tractate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
Saint <hi>Iohn.</hi> And therefore if he that murders a mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
deſerues death, how much more hee that deſtroyes a
mans ſoule. Or if they which were murderers of the Lord
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10126:14"/>
Ieſus in reſpect of his body deſerued to dye, how much
more they which ſeeke to murder his holy ſpirit. Thirdly,
the <hi>Turke</hi> himſelfe (as one truely ſaith) cannot ſo much
hurt or endamage the Church of God as an haereticke may:<note place="margin">Nec turca tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumdamni infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re pateſt Eccleſiae quantum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticus. Ferus in mat.</note>
and therefore if it be lawfull to put to death common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
of our liues in warre, why is it not lawfull for the
Magiſtrate to put to death the enemies of our ſoules, of
God, and of the State.</p>
               <p>Againe, we haue diuers examples of this lawfull ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie
executed vpon Idolaters in former ages. Firſt, in <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah,</hi>
in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18. 40. commanding all the Prophets of
<hi>Baal</hi> to be ſlaine. Secondly, in <hi>Iehu,</hi> in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10. 24, 25.
giuing the like command concerning the worſhippers of
<hi>Baal.</hi> Thirdly, in all the inhabitants of the land of <hi>Iuda,</hi> in
2 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 18. who deſtroyed all the houſes of <hi>Baal,</hi> and
ſlue <hi>Mattan</hi> the Prieſt before the Altars.</p>
               <p>Furthermore we haue examples alſo in the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Hiſtorie: Firſt, in <hi>Constantine</hi> that famous Chriſtian
Emperour, who enacted a ſtatute, as appeares by a<note n="c" place="margin">Apud Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger decad. 2. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. 8.</note> letter
of his written to one <hi>Taurus,</hi> That if any did offer Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
vpon the Altars: <hi>gladio vltore ſterneretur:</hi> he ſhould
be put to death by the ſword, and his goods confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.
The like was enacted by<note n="c" place="margin">In Codice Theodoſiano tit. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinianus,</hi>
by <hi>Martianus</hi> alſo, as the ſame <hi>Henry Bullin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi>
recordeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the ground and warrant of this is the good word
of God: for the Lord himſelfe ſaith,</hi> Deut. 13. 5. that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
or dreamer of Dreames ſhall be put to death, becauſe
he hath ſpoken to turne you away from the Lord your God:
<hi>and in verſ.</hi> 9. thou ſhalt ſurely kill him, thine hand ſhall be
firſt vpon him to put him to death, and afterward the hand of
all the people. <hi>And againe in verſ.</hi> 10. thou ſhalt ſtone him
with ſtones that he dye, becauſe hee hath ſought to thrust
thee away from the Lord thy God. <hi>Now if any ſhall ſay
this was a Iudiciall Law giuen to the Iſraelites. I anſwer,
ſay it were ſo, yet the equitie of that Iudiciall Law remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
ſtill to all Nations. The like proofe we haue in</hi> Zech.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10126:14"/>
13. 3. it ſhall come to paſſe that when any ſhall yet propheſie,
then his Father and his Mother that begat him, ſhall thruſt
him through when he propheſieth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Epiſtol. 48.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> indeed wauered concerning the like
point for a time as he himſelfe confeſſeth in one of his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
but when he ſaw that the City wherein he dwelt was
reclaimed from Donatiſme by the ſword of the Magiſtrate,
hee reuerſed his opinion, and confeſſed that Heretickes
might lawfully bee enforced and puniſhed by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
               <p>But if any ſhall obiect,<note place="margin">Obiection.</note> that in the new Teſtament wee
are exhorted indeed to flye the company of Heretickes,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17. not to receiue them into our houſes, 2 Epiſt.
Iohn verſe 10. after the firſt and ſecond admonition to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
them, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2. 10.</p>
               <p>And heere in my Text to beware of them, but no
where to put any of them to death,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> I anſwer, at that time
when the New Teſtament was penned, and alſo when our
bleſſed Sauiour liued vpon the earth and preached, the
Church of God was vnder the tyrannie of the Romane
Empire: ſo that it had bin in vaine at that time to haue
ſtirred it vp to put falſe Prophets to death, the hands of the
Church being then bound; neither was it abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie
to vſe any ſuch excitation, becauſe there was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
direction giuen already in the Old Teſtament, what
was to be done concerning hereticall Seducers: and yet it
is to be obſerued, that the Church euen in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
wiſhed that ſeducers were cut off, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 12. vpon
the which place, one of the<note n="c" place="margin">S. Ambroſe non ſolum ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliter ſed etiam carnaliter hos maledicit.</note> antients ſaith, the Apoſtle in
this Text of Scripture doth not onely wiſh a ſpirituall
cutting off to the ſeducers of his time, but alſo a corporall
abſciſſion: he deſires that as they were a meanes to put
the Galatians to bodily paine by vrging Circumciſion vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, ſo that they themſelues might bee put to bodily
paine by vtter cutting off their very liues: where that
reuerend Father vſeth an accuſatiue caſe <hi>hos</hi> of the perſon
after maledicit after the manner of the <hi>eccleſiaſtici Scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:10126:15"/>
whoſe faſhion it is, as a learned<note n="e" place="margin">Deſpauterius in Syntax.</note> Gramarian ſpeakes,
to put accuſatiue caſes of the perſon after verbes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
with <hi>benè</hi> or <hi>malè:</hi> but to let the conſtruction
paſſe and to returne to the matter: here wee ſee in Saint
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> his iudgement, that the Church in the Apoſtles
time, though it had not preſent power to put ſeducers to
death, yet it wiſhed that they were put to death: and if
the Church in thoſe daies wiſhed their death, it would as
well haue put them to death if it had not beene reſtreined
by ouer-ruling tyrannie; as it is more then probable.</p>
               <p>I might be large in this ſubiect, but I muſt <hi>instar canis
aegyptiaci</hi> content my ſelfe with a lap or two of this Nilus,
for feare of being ſtung by the Crocodile of raſh cenſure
for my tediouſneſſe: therefore for breuity ſake I referre
the learned Reader to that learned booke<note n="c" place="margin">De haereticis a ciuili Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu puniendis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Martini Bellij farragine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; nouorum ac a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam.</note> of <hi>Theodore
Beza,</hi> the title wherof you haue in the margent wherin he
proues by impregnable arguments, That hereticks may be
Lawfully puniſhed by the Ciuill Magiſtrates, yea and if
they cannot by any other meanes be reclaimed, they may
iuſtly be put to death, as<note n="e" place="margin">Teſte Caluiſio lib opus chron.</note> 
                  <hi>Seruetus</hi> was at <hi>Geneuah, Anno</hi>
1553.</p>
               <p>Now what I haue ſaid in this queſtion concerning the
puniſhment of hereticall ſeducers may iuſtly be applyed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
to blaſphemers of God. For if they which denie fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall
truth and oppoſe it with obſtinacy deſerue
death, how much more they which blaſpheme it and the
author of it which is God and Chriſt: and therefore if any
miſcreant Iew or other ſhall come impudently amongſt vs
Chriſtians, and like another Goliath ſhall defie our Sauiour
as he did the hoſt of the liuing God: ſurely our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
vpon iuſt proofe may lawfully put him to death:
May? Yea ought ſo to doe. God himſelfe maketh blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
capitall, or death-deſeruing in expreſſe termes, <hi>Leuit.</hi>
24. 16. and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 29. makes a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,
that if any of what Tongue or Nation ſoeuer, ſhall
ſpeake any thing amiſſe (as you haue it in the Engliſh
Tranſlation) againſt the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach,</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10126:15"/>
                  <hi>Abednego,</hi> he ſhall be cut in pieces, and his houſe ſhall be
made a dung-hill: the originall words in that Text, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
the Caldee, ſhew the ſtrictneſſe of that ſtatute: for
whereas it is tranſlated ſhall ſpeake any thing amiſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> in the
Caldee it is ſhall ſpeake an error: intimating thereby that
if any did ſpeake blaſphemie though it might poſſibly be
pretended, that he did ſo out of error of iudgement: yet
by the ſentence of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> (in that no doubt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
in the maine by the Spirit of God) he was to die
for it: and if a Heathen King was thus zealous for
God againſt Blaſphemers, how much more doth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houe
Chriſtian Princes to bee zealous: but I leaue this
point: and thus I haue done with the firſt part of my Text,
to wit, the Caueat of our Sauiour giuen to his Church
concerning Falſe Prophets, in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>:
<hi>Beware yee of pſeudoprophets.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Which come, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHich come vnto you in ſheeps clothing.</hi> In this firſt
Deſcription we haue three things to be obſerued
concerning Falſe Prophets. Firſt, their intruſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
they come vnſent. Secondly, their inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> they come to Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
not to the common multitude. Thirdly, their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> they come
diſguized and not in their owne likeneſſe. For the firſt,
that they are meere intruders into the office of teaching,
and haue no lawfull calling thereunto, it is apparant in
<hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 21. <hi>I haue not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ranne, I
haue not ſpoken vnto them, yet they propheſied:</hi> they haue
no calling from God. 1. Becauſe either they are meerely
ignorant and vnſufficient to be guides, as many are which
take vpon them to be teachers amongſt the Anabaptiſts
and Familiſts being vnlearned men taken out of ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10126:16"/>
trade, or ſecondly, becauſe they haue not a right miniſterial
affection, but aime at their owne priuate ends, to wit, to
rob, kill, &amp; to deſtroy, as our Sauiour ſaith of them, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.
10. or thirdly, becauſe they hold and teach fundamentall
errors, which plainely argueth that they are guided by the
ſpirit of Satan, and not by Gods Spirit. Furthermore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
they haue no calling from the Church, yea, they
contemne that calling as idle and impertinent, being like
thoſe ſeducers ſpoken of, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 24. which went out and
taught the Gentiles, the Apoſtles giuing them no ſuch
Commandement.</p>
               <p>I will not inſiſt vpon this point, yet it may ſerue as a
ſtrong motiue to diſſwade men and women from
hearing theſe vnſent ſeducers: for if they be not ſent
of God, why ſhould any dare to heare them, yea what
good can any man expect to receiue by ſuch teachers; and
yet ſuch is the folly of many at theſe times, that they had
rather heare a man without calling in ſome priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticle,
then a true miniſter ſent of God and authorized
by the Church in a lawfull aſſembly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Vnto you.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VNto you,</hi> that is vnto you my Diſciples: whence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
me, what kinde of people hereticall teachers
deſire eſpecially to ſeduce, namely<note n="c" place="margin">Qui Lupira pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces niſi ſpiritus ſubdoli ad infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandum gregem Chriſti intrinſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus deliteſcentes. Tertul. lib. de praeſcript.</note> Chriſt his Diſciples, or
ſuch as are liuing members of the Church. This is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
by that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 24. where we haue falſe Chriſts,
and falſe Prophets going about to deceiue if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
the very elect, and by that in <hi>Reu.</hi> 2. 20. where we haue
the Romiſh Ieſabel (for of her I take it, is typically ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in that place) ſeducing Gods ſeruants: we may alſo ſee
it daily verified by very experience for whom do Familiſts,
Anabaptiſts and other Sectaries commonly labour to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert
and ſeduce? Not Drunkards, Adulterers, Sabbath-breakers,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10126:16"/>
Gamſters, Lyers, Swearers and ſuch like, but
rather ſuch as ſeeme to be conuerted, which mourne for
their ſins and deſire to know the right way to heauen, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
bin in ſome meaſure wrought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the publike mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery
of the Church: wherein ſeducers are like vnto kites,
which flie vp and downe to ceaze vpon tender Chickens,
or rather like vnto their father the Diuell, who loues to
come in amongſt Gods children, <hi>Iob</hi> 2. 1. not for loue of
their perſons, much leſſe of the exerciſes of Religion, but
to accompliſh his owne ends, which may ſerue for a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat
to all tender Chriſtians, to teach them the more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
to looke to themſelues: but I will not further inſiſt
vpon this point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in ſheeps clothing,</hi> that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>in ſheepes skinnes:</hi> for what is the cloathing
of a ſilly ſheepe but its skinne or fell: in this Deſcription
of Falſe Prophets, our Sauiour may ſeeme to allude to the
Woolfe in the Fable: concerning the whcih the Mytholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt
ſpeaketh thus:<note place="margin">Lupus <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uis pelle indutus ouium ſe immiſcuit gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi quotidieque aliquam ex eis occidebat quod cum paſtor ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madue<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiſſet illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in altiſſima arbore ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, interrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus autem cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris paſtoribus cur ouem ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet aiebat peb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis quidem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> videtis eſt ouis opera autem Lupi.</note> a Woolfe on a time putting on a ſheepes
skinne immingled himſelfe amongſt the Flocke, and ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
day ſtrangled ſome of the ſheepe, which when the
ſhepheard perceiued, he tooke the Wolfe and hanged him
vp in an high tree: at the which when other ſhepheards
ignorant of the cauſe wondered, and demanded of their
fellow-ſhepheard what hee meant to be ſo cruell to hang
vp a ſilly harmeleſſe ſheepe; he anſwered: his skinne as you
ſee is the skinne of a ſheepe, but his workes are the works
of a Woolſe: vnto the which it is not altogether improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
(for I will not be peremptory in alluſions) that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
in my Text doth in ſome ſort allude, no more then
it is improbable that S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth allude to the olympian
games in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 23, 24, 25. where he ſpeakes of running
of a race for a corruptible Crowne: neither is it in any ſort
impoſſible for Chriſt to haue this alluſion, <hi>Aeſop</hi> the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thologiſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10126:17"/>
liuing almoſt 600 yeeres before him as <hi>Buchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerus</hi>
notes out of<note n="c" place="margin">Euſebius &amp; Suidas.</note> two ſubſtantiall Authors in his <hi>index
Chronologicus;</hi> and the words of the Text ſo iuſtly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:
<hi>Beware of Falſe Prophets which come vnto you in
ſheepes clothing, but inwardly they are rauening Wolues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In ſheepes clothing:</hi> wherein we may obſerue that it is
not the manner of ſeducers ordinarily to appeare outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
what they are within, but if they be birds of the prey
they will ſeeme to be doues, if they be ſtinging Serpents,
they will ſeeme to be harmeleſſe wormes, if they bee tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culent
Wolues they will ſeeme to be innocent ſheepe, in a
word; if they be<note n="e" place="margin">Introrſum turpes ſpecioſi pelle de<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ora.</note> foule within they will be faire without:
and the reaſon of this hypocriſie in ſeducers in manifeſt,
becauſe as it is with a Wolfe, if he ſhould come howling to
the ſheepefold and in his owne skinne the watchfull ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard
would reſiſt him with his crooke and with his dog,
but putting on a ſheeps skinne and counterfeiting the
bleating of a ſheepe, hee findes entertainement, and the
ſheepe ſhunne him not, but delight to walke with him, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
he plucke out their throates: euen ſo pernicious ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,
if they ſhould come in their owne likeneſſe, they
know the Magiſtrates and Miniſters would withſtand
them, and the people would ſhunne them, and flie from
them: but comming in the name of zealous Chriſtians,
they are leſſe ſuſpected, and leſſe ſhunned and oppoſed:
yea, with ſome they finde kinde entertainement, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
a good report. I ſpeake this to the ſhame of many
in our times, which haue not learned to put difference (ſo
ignorant are they of the doctrine of Religion) betweene a
palliated Woolfe, and a true Orthodox ſheepe of Ieſus
Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:10126:17"/>
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <head type="sub">In ſheepes cloathing.</head>
               <p>HEere it may be demanded, what is meant by <hi>ſheepes
cloathing;</hi> or in what manner, cunning ſeducers come
in that rayment. I anſwer, Seducers come in ſheepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.
Firſt, when they come with quotations out of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Scripture, to confirme their damnable poſitions: thus
the diuell came to our Sauiour in ſheepes clothing, when
he came with a <hi>ſic ſcriptum eſt, Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>for it is written,
he will giue his Angels charge ouer thee, &amp;c.</hi> and thus Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts,
and Anabaptiſts come in ſheepes clothing, which
vſe to bring Scripture peruerted to proue their tenents, as
though the Scripture of truth did in any ſort fauour their
errors: and thus <hi>Arius</hi> came in ſheepes clothing, of whom
I haue read, that he brought 42 places out of the Scripture
to proue, that Chriſt was meere man and not God, againſt
<hi>Athanaſius</hi> that diſputed with him in the Nicaean Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when they come vnder a pretence of hauing
all antiquity on their ſides, fauouring their hereticall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
deceiuing the world as the Gibeonites deceiued <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua</hi>
with old bottels, and old ſhooes, and mouldy bread,
and old garments, as though they had come from farre,
when as indeed they were but of the next towne. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 9. 11,
12. Thus <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and other Controuerſiſts amongſt
the Papiſts come as Woolues in ſheepes clothing, when
they impudently affirme that all antiquity is on their ſides,
that all the Fathers, and Councels, and Doctors ſpeake for
them and the like; which hath beene proued falſe to their
faces by many of our<note n="c" place="margin">Whitakers. Chamierus, Willet and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others.</note> learned Diuines, which haue taken
paines to confute them, and this ſhewes, that they haue
browes of braſſe to boaſt of antiquity, when as the maine
abominations of Popery were firſt hatched by the Trent-Councell,
or rather the Trent-Conſpiracie, hardly yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10126:18"/>
an 100 yeeres agoe, and were not ſo much as knowne to
the Fathers which liued in the firſt 500 yeeres after Chriſt.
I pittie their ſoules that are ſo enthraled to ſuch guides, as
that they muſt beleeue whatſoeuer they tell them without
any further diſquiſition, and ſo muſt content themſelues
with the colyars faith, to beleeue as the Church beleeues,
though they know not what the Church beleeueth. I pitty
them, I ſay, becauſe they are as ſheepe committing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
to the keeping of a Woolfe, as it is in the<note n="e" place="margin">Apud Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ouem Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po commiſiſti in Eunucho act. 5. ſcen. 1.</note> comaedie,
and I will ſtill pray that God would deliuer them out the
iawes of theſe foul-deuouring Woolues; and that hee
would cauſe the light of his owne Goſpell to ſhine into
their hearts, whereby the darke miſts of ignorance and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition
may bee diſpelled and aboliſhed, that ſo they
may receiue the truth in the loue of it, to their owne eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
benefit, and the comfort of others.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when they come with plauſible bookes, ſuch
bookes as ſeeme to haue many good things in them, but
ſome bad, ſuch bookes as haue ſome phiſicke and ſome
poyſon,<note place="margin">Lib. 15. moral. c. 10. habent hoc haretici propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um vt bona malis puniſceant. Sicut qui veneni poculum porrigit, ora poculi dulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine melius tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git.</note> ſome wheate and ſome tares: for it is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of Heretickes as <hi>Gregory</hi> notes to mingle ſome good
things amongſt their bad, euen as a cunning poyſoner
when he meanes to poyſon another man with ſome dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
wine, he firſt annointeth the lip of the cup with ſweet
hony: thus the moſt Heretickes and Seducers come in
ſheepes clothing, by giuing ſeducing bookes as a great
preſent to ſuch as they meane to ſeduce: their bandy
bookes being like the<note n="c" place="margin">Aenaeads 9.</note> Troiane horſe in Vergil, which
was pretended to be the gift of <hi>Minerua,</hi> but it wrought
the ruine of <hi>Troy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, when they come as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of
them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 18. with good words and flattering ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
pretending to tender our good, and to counſell vs
for the beſt, to wiſh our ſaluation, &amp;c. and yet vnder that
coulour, labour to ſeduce vs: for as a learned<note n="c" place="margin">Gregorius magnus lib. 23. moral. c. 21. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici ſub ſpecie conſulendi agu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t negotium ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi.</note> Father
ſpeaketh: Heretickes vnder a colour of giuing good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
doe indeed ſeduce men: thus likewiſe all ſeducers come
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10126:18"/>
to the Church of God in ſheepes Cloathing, for they
all pretend to giue good and ſauing Counſell: when
as their breath is as the poyſon of Aſpes, and as it is
ſaid of the Baſiliske, that hee kills with his looke, or
with the beames that come from his poyſonfull eyes,
euen ſo theſe kill with their mouthes by the poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
breath which procedeth from the ſame; according
to that <hi>Adders poyſon is vnder their lips,</hi> Selah. <hi>Pſalme</hi>
140. 3.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, when they come with the whole ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
or outſide of a Chriſtian profeſſion as<note n="e" place="margin">Tertullian lib. de praeſcriptioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. Superficies Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani nomini<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> extrinſecus.</note> one of the
ancients ſpeakes, to wit, with an outward expreſſion
of holineſſe, with a ſeeming contempt of the world,
with prayers, faſtings, teares, almeſ-deeds, ſeeming
zeale, comely geſtures, ſeeming loue, ſeeming pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
ſeeming conformitie, ſeeming humilitie, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
harmeleſneſſe and the like; for it is not vnuſuall with
Seducers to diſſemble an honeſt life, as<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Theop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad loc.</note> one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
ſaith: thus the Herodians and Diſciples of the
Phariſees came to our Sauiour in ſheepes cloathing, <hi>Luke</hi>
20. 20. counterfeiting themſelues to bee iuſt men, and
thus of all other Sects vnder the Sunne, the hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall
Sect of the Familiſts, together with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades
the Anabaptiſts come amongſt vs Chriſtians in
ſheepes cloathing: for they will carry themſelues<note n="c" place="margin">Hypocriſis mentitur curioſa, hypocriſie is ſpun with a fine thred. Chryſolog. ſer. 7.</note> ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
as though they were very zealous and good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
when as in the meane time by their pernicious
Doctrine and priuate Counſell, they cut the very
throate of the Goſpell and of the true Church of
CHRIST: the Vſe of this followes in the next
Section.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:10126:19"/>
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN ſheepes cloathing:</hi> it being ſo that ſeducers come as
Woolues in ſheepes cloathing, this may teach vs diuers
things:</p>
               <p>Firſt, to take notice of the wofull condition of ſuch Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites,
they are Chriſts ſheepe onely in outward ſhew,
not in heart, they are whited Sepulchers, a meere outſide,
a painted abhomination. The Lord may ſay of their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
ſhew, as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Coate, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37 33. <hi>this
Coate is the Coate of my Sonne, ſome enill beaſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured
him.</hi> So this outward forme of godlineſſe is the
outward forme of my ſonnes and daughters, but ſome
euill ſpirit hath deuoured them which vſe it in Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it ſerues iuſtly to roproue many of our times,
who for want of iudgement being blinded with affection,
are ready to iuſtifie erroneous perſons for a meere outward
hypocriticall ſhew, be their doctrines and opinions neuer
ſo pernicious and hereticall; which is as if a fooliſh man or
woman ſhould commend a Woolfe to be an innocent and
harmeleſſe creature, becauſe hee hath put on a Sheepes-skinne.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it ſerues to teach ſuch as make ſhew of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
to take notice that a meere outſide in Religion is
not ſufficient in Gods ſight: an Hypocrite, yea a damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
ſeducer may haue an outſide, he may come in a ſheepes
skinne as we haue heard: but wee muſt labour for an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
heart: for God aboue all reſpecteth that.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, it ſerues to teach Chriſtians to bee the more
wary with whom they do conuerſe, and whom they heare,
eſpecially to beware of priuate conuenticles, leaſt whilſt
they thinke to conuerſe with true ſheepe, they meete with
Woolues in ſheepes clothing.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, it ſerues to teach Gouernors to bee the more
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10126:19"/>
warie, when cunning ſeducers come before them, for as
theſe Wolues haue their ſheepes clothing to deceiue the
people withall, ſo they haue their outward yeelding to
conformity, their equiuocations, their externall ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
and the like, wherewith to deceiue authority and to
rid themſelues out of trouble. <hi>Arius</hi> was knowne to
yeeld to the Nicaeane Councell as appeares by a Letter of
ſubmiſſion which he wrote to Conſtantine the Great: the
which Letter is noted by<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. Sancti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onum.</note> 
                  <hi>Iouerius</hi> in the Deſcription of
the Nicaean Councell: but his yeelding was meerely Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall
to rid himſelfe out of trouble, for he reteined his
blaſphemous opinions ſtill, and diſperſed them in priuate
more then before. I confeſſe the Magiſtrates cannot doe
leſſe (I meane the Church-Gouernors) then receiue peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
perſons vpon their ſubmiſſion into the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.
I acknowledge alſo that the boſome of the Church
ſhould be alwaies open to humbled and contrite perſons.
But becauſe Hypocriticall ſeducers may make it a practice
to deceiue Magiſtrates by fained ſubmiſſion, therefore the
ſafeſt courſe is (which ſtands alſo with iuſtice) to inflict
vpon them condigne puniſhment for their former diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances,
and then if after their due puniſhment they
wil ſubmit and deſire to be receiued, to receiue them vpon
further tryall, I ſay vpon further tryall, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
as it is in the Prouerbe, the Woolfe
may change his haire, but he will hardly change his minde
or nature: and thus much may ſuffice for the firſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
of Falſe Prophets, which is by their outward ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
or externall ſhew, in theſe words, <hi>which come vnto you
in ſheepes Cloathings.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:10126:20"/>
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">But inwardly they are rauening Woolues.</head>
               <p>IN theſe words wee haue the ſecond Deſcription
of ſeducers, and as the former was by their outward
ſhew, ſo this is by their inward quality: <hi>Inwardly
they are rauening Wolues:</hi> wherein two things are
to bee obſerued concerning hereticall ſeducers: Firſt, that
they are Wolues: Secondly, that they are rauenous.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, that they are Wolues, that is of a lupine
or Woluiſh diſpoſition, is manifeſt, not onely by the
words of the Text, but alſo by that in <hi>Acts</hi> 20 29. where
they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> grieuous Wolues, or if you
will, fat Wolues, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Greeke comes of
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in Hebrew, which ſignifies fat as ſome Etymologiſts
haue obſerued, a fit Epithite for ſeducers, which fat
themſelues with the blood of ſoules.</p>
               <p>And hereticall Seducers are fitly compared to
Wolues in diuers reſpects: Firſt, becauſe as Wolues
are dull-ſighted in the day, but quick-ſighted in the
night, as<note n="c" place="margin">Lupus interdiu obtuſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s nocte clarius videt.</note> one ſaith of them: euen ſo pernicious Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers
are oftentimes very acute and ſharp-witted for
error,<note n="d" place="margin">Conrad. Geſner lib. 1. de quadru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</note> they are able in their faſhion, (hauing their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine
witts commonly exerciſed about nothing elſe)
to diſpute for that, yea very idiots (ſuch as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts,
and Anabaptiſts bee) will bee brabbling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Learned Miniſters, <hi>in puluere olympico,</hi> ſo
farre as the engliſh skill will extend, but they are
dull to apprehend the truth of ſound Diuinitie, yea,
they ſhut their eyes like Owles againſt that ſhining
light.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as the Woolfe deales<note n="d" place="margin">Lupus cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouem rapuerit de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus eam non laedit ſed ſuper dorſi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ſuum eam ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiter iacêre fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, vincent in ſpecul, nat lib. 19 c. 83.</note> gently with the ſheepe
at the firſt, carrying it away vnhurt vpon his backe, vntill
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10126:20"/>
he haue brought it to the place where he meanes to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
it. Euen ſo pernicious ſeducers vſe to deale with their
Proſelytes, at the firſt drawing them into lighter errors,
but afterwards like grieuous Wolues, plucking out the
throat of their ſoules, by leading them into blaſphemous
and damnable haereſies: and thus <hi>homo homini Lupus eſt,</hi>
one man becomes a Woolfe to another.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, as a Woolfe begets a Woolfe, according to that
rule in nature,<note place="margin">Omne ſimile ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat. ſibi ſimile.</note> euery like begets his like: euen ſo peruici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
ſeducers ſpiritually beget ſuch as proue like vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
both in opinion and practiſe, and indeede they
which are conuerted, or rather peruerted by haereticall
ſpirits, whatſoeuer high conceits they may haue of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
they are but of ſeeming Sheepe made reall
Wolues.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Voce deſeratur is quem prior vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit Lupus Plin. l. 8. nat. hiſt. c. 22.</note> as the Wolfe is ſaid to ſtrike a man dumbe, if
he ſpie the man before the man ſpie him: euen ſo when
ſeducers preuaile, they ſtrike men dumbe, in reſpect of any
true profeſſion of Chriſtianity; yea, they bring them by
their ſeductions to blaſpheme all ſound profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, as the wooll of a Woolfe, if it be made into a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
will proue but an odious garment,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. c Lib. 2. Sympoſ. q 9.</note> breeding ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
vpon him that ſhall weare it inſtead of miniſtring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
comfort, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeakes: euen ſo the good which
poore ſeduced ſoules thinke they receiue by impoſtors,
and deceiuers of mindes,<note place="margin">Lupi toto anno non amplius qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duodecim diebus coeunt. Iſid. Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal. lib. 12. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum. c. 2.</note> it will proue corruption in
the end.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, as the Woolfe maketh ſhew of ciuile vertue, as
of chaſtitie and the like, congreſſing but onely 12. dayes in
a whole yeare. Euen ſo the moſt pernicious ſeducers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
make ſhew of much ciuilitie and moralitie, and
thereby they doe more harme amongſt the ignorant ſort
then by any other meanes. Whereupon one of the<note n="c" place="margin">Orig hom. 7. in Ez<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k. Sollicitè caueamuus hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticos qui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſationis, opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſunt, quorum fortè vitam non tam Deus quam diabolus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruxit.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
ſaith notably; let vs be exceeding wary of thoſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes
which are of the beſt conuerſation, whoſe liues poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
are directed not of God, but of the diuell. And thus
we ſee for what reaſons hereticall ſeducers are fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10126:21"/>
pared vnto Wolues. I might adde another, taken from the
rauenouſneſſe of Wolues, but that I reſerue for the next
Section. Come we now to the vſe of the point.</p>
               <p>And it being demonſtrated that haereticall ſeducers are
Wolues, it firſt ſerues not onely to iuſtifie againſt all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniators,
but alſo much to commend the lawfull ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
of Courts of Iuſtice againſt ſuch.<note n="c" place="margin">Sicut eſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordia puniens ita eſt crudelitas parcens Epiſt. 54.</note> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi>
ſaith, there is a puniſhing mercy, and a ſparing crueltie.
This may ſeeme to be a paradox to ſome, but the father
knew what he ſaid: for it is a puniſhing mercie when wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
Gouernours doe puniſh dangerous ſeducers for the
ſafetie of the whole, and it were a ſparing crueltie to let
them paſſe vnpuniſhed; for looke how much mercy is
ſhewed to the Wolfe, ſo much crueltie is done to the Sheep,
yea it is mercy to ſeducers themſelues (if they could skill
of it) that the Gouernors ſeeke to reſtraine them from
their damnable wayes, by inflicting iuſt puniſhment vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them, this being the laſt meanes that the Church can
vſe to cure them: according to that of <hi>Aristotle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 2. Ethic. c. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
are kindes of medicines; but howſoeuer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers
themſelues and their court-flandering adherents
doe take it, I am ſure all good people haue great cauſe to
praiſe God for the zeale of our Gouernours, in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect:
our bodies might as ſafely liue in a roring wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
in the midſt of Wolues and Tygers, as our ſoules in
our ſtrongeſt Cities amongſt ſeducers, if there were not
Courts of Iuſtice to ſuppreſſe them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it makes for the iuſt reproofe of many at
theſe dayes, who when they haue dangerous Wolues diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered
vnto them, will not lend their helping hand to
ſuppreſſe them for the common ſafetie of the Church, but
ſuffer them to walke vp and downe in the very Sheepfold
without reſiſtance. Gods cauſe and his truth for the which
they ought to contend, <hi>Iud.</hi> 3. is little beholding to them,
I pray God it be not one day ſaid to their charge: a bad
cauſe oftentimes findes much patronage; the wicked will
ſtraine their purſes, try their friends, put themſelues to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10126:21"/>
great paines for the ſupporting of it; but the cauſe of God
may ſinke or ſwim (were it not for good Gouernours) for
any helpe or countenance that the forward men of our
time, for the moſt part will giue vnto it. If it were noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly
knowne that ſome deuouring Wolfe did haunt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
this Citie, which had deſtroyed an 100. perſons, I
ſuppoſe euery man would lay it to heart, and vſe the beſt
meanes he could to ſuppreſſe ſuch a noyſome creature:
are we thus carefull for the common ſafetie of mens liues,
and ſhall there be no care for the common ſafetie of their
ſoules? Is it ſo heinous a matter when an hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
are corporally ſtrangled, and is it nothing when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
hundreds are ſpiritually murdered? But I imagine
what you will ſay; why ſhould wee put our finger in the
fire? why ſhould we meddle in a controuerſie which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
vs not? I anſwer, if the controuerſie indeede were
a meere priuate controuerſie, you ſeeme to ſay ſome thing;
but if it be a publike controuerſie, and concerne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
ſafetie, your obiection or plea is little worth.</p>
               <p>But many haue learned that Greeke Prouerbe in our
times, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it is good ſleeping in a
whole skin: yea ſome are ſuch valiant champions, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
ingaged in the Lords controuerſie, will vſe meanes
and friends to draw their owne heads out of the collar,
and leaue others to endure the whole brunt of the battell
and danger. Such white-liuerd Soldiers are fit to take
the <hi>Salmacida ſpolia</hi> which<note n="c" place="margin">In officijs,</note> 
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeakes of; ſpoiles
which are obtained <hi>fine ſanguine &amp; ſudore:</hi> if victorie will
come of it ſelfe without paines or peril it ſhal be welcome;
if not, they loue not to contend for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 12.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <head type="sub">Rauening.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RAuening.</hi> Hence obſerue we, that <hi>Seducers are of a
rauenous diſpoſition.</hi> In which very reſpect they are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10126:22"/>
alſo compared vnto Wolues, in the words of my Text.
And it is famouſly noted by Heathen Phyloſophers (who
had a great gift in looking farre into the natures of the
creatures) that the Wolfe of all other beaſts is the moſt
rauenous.<note n="c" place="margin">Ouid. l. 1. triſt. Eleg. 1. excuſſa eſt auidis dentibus Agna Lupi.</note> One ſaith (making it a wonder) the tender
Lambe is ſhaken out of the greedy teeth of the Woolfe:
deſcribing the Woolfe as a greedy creature. Another ſaith
that the Wolfe endures winde and weather,<note n="i" place="margin">Virgil. AEnead. 9. ventos per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſſus &amp; imbres nocte ſuper me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</note> raine and
ſtormie tempeſts, and that at midnight, to watch for his
prey. Thus the poets ſing concerning the rauenouſneſſe
of the Woolfe: and in like manner others write in proſe:
<note n="n" place="margin">Lib. 11. nat. hiſt. c. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith of the Wolues called <hi>Ceruarij</hi> that they are
vnſatiable, they can neuer be ſufficed or haue enough.
<note n="m" place="margin">Lib. 1. de quadrup.</note> 
                  <hi>Conradus Geſner</hi> ſaith of the Wolfe called <hi>Circus,</hi> that
hee is <hi>ſemper famelicus,</hi> alwaies hungrie. And <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>
declaring the opinion of all men concerning the
Woolfe hath this report <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Ariſtot. lib. 8. de hiſtor animal. c. 5.</note>
They ſay of Wolues that for hunger ſome times
they will eate the very earth; yea, the Woolfe beares ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenouſneſſe
in the very forehead of his etymologie: for
the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, commonly vſed for a Woolfe: either comes
of the Greeke Theame <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies <hi>dilanio,</hi> to
teare in peeces, or of the Hebrew root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifieth
<hi>abſorbeo,</hi> to ſwallow downe: both importing gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe.</p>
               <p>And hereticall ſeducers are like vnto Wolues in this
reſpect: being commonly ſuch as hunger after worldly
gaine, according to that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 18. <hi>they that are ſuch
ſerue not our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but their owne bellies.</hi> And
ſuch alſo as thirſt after the bloud of ſoules, compaſſing
Sea and Land to make a Proſelyte, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 15.</p>
               <p>Which may ſerue to teach vs: Firſt, that the deſire of
winning of ſoules is not alwayes the marke of a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
a falſe Prophet may hunger and thirſt to winne ſoules
to his owne faction, but a ſincere deſire to gaine ſoules
to Chriſt, and to his truth: this is a badge of a true
Shepheard.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:10126:22"/>
Secondly, this may ſerue to forewarne Gods children
to looke to themſelues the more carefully, and to commit
themſelues the more feruently by prayer daily to Gods
ſpeciall protection, conſidering their deſtruction is ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
after by many rauenous ſeducers.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it muſt teach vs that ſtill remaine in the truth
vnſtrangled by the rauenous Welues of the time, to bleſſe
God for it: and to ſay of our ſpirituall deliuerance as the
Church ſaith of her corporall, in Pſalme 124. if it had not
beene the Lord who was on our ſide: now may Iſrael ſay,
if it had not beene the Lord who was on our ſide, when
men roſe vp againſt vs;—then they had ſwallowed vs vp
quicke; but bleſſed be the Lord who hath not giuen vs
as a prey to their teeth.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the intent of the Text, or of the Text in
generall. The Extent followeth.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The occaſion of all which followeth.</head>
                  <p>THis which followeth was added becauſe an order of
ſubmiſſion or recantation was enioyned by the moſt
reuerend Father in God, the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terburie</hi>
his grace, and other his Maieſties Commiſſioners
Eccleſiaſticall vnto one <hi>Iohn Hetherington,</hi> late of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and now of <hi>Putney</hi> in the Countie of
<hi>Surrie,</hi> to be performed by him the ſame day this Sermon
was preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, being the eleanenth day of
February, <hi>Anno</hi> 1627. when it was ordered that the ſaid
<hi>Hetherington</hi> vpon Sonday the 11. day of February ſhould
before the beginning of the Sermon at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe come
within the wall there iuſt before the Pulpit, and there
ſtand before the Preacher, bare-faced and bare-headed in
ſome eminent place, where hee might be beſt ſeene and
heard of the Congregation aſſembled during the whole
time of the Sermon, hauing a paper on his breaſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
his offence in theſe words; <hi>for ſcandalizing the whole
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10126:23"/>
Church of England, in ſaying it is no true Church of Chriſt,
and publiſhing other erronious opinions, proceeding from
that ill ground:</hi> for the which cauſe he was enioyned this
acknowledgement.</p>
                  <p>Whereas I <hi>Iohn Hetherington</hi> ſtand by the depoſitions
of ſundry witneſſes iudicially conuicted before the Kings
Maieſties Commiſſioners appointed for Cauſes Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall,
for that ſince the 20. of December 1623. I haue
maintained and publiſhed, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> as
it is now by the Law eſtabliſhed, is no true Church of
Chriſt, and that it teacheth falſe Doctrine, that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
day or Sunday, which we commonly call the Lords
day, ſince the Apoſtles time was of no force, and that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
day is a Sabbath as much as that which we call the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
day, the Lords day or Sunday: that the Bookes of
<hi>Eſdras</hi> are and ought to be eſteemed part of the Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Scripture: as alſo to haue vſed reproachfull words to
and of the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of
their calling. And further, whereas it ſtandeth proued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
me, that being by trade a Boxmaker about fiue or
ſix yeeres ſince I gaue ouer my ſaid trade, and frequented
priuate Conuenticles, by the Lawes of this Realme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited,
taking vpon me within the time articulated to be
the chiefe Speaker and to inſtruct others, not being of
mine owne familie in points of Doctrine, and matters of
faith, giuing expoſitions contrary to the receiued opinions
of this our Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in defence of ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles
haue ſaid or writ that <hi>Caeſar</hi> may command a
place in publike, ſo as he forbid none in priuate. As alſo
that i haue bin of opinion with the Familiſts touching the
perfect puritie of the foule, with ſome other erronious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions
mentioned in the proofes. For the which I haue
bin impriſoned by the order of his Maieſties Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
Eccleſiaſticall, and haue beene enioyned to make this
my publike Recantation or ſubmiſſion here this day. I doe
therefore before you all here preſent from my heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce,
abiure, and diſclaime all the ſaid opinions as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10126:23"/>
and ſchiſmaticall, and doe promiſe from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
not to entermeddle in the keeping or frequenting of
any priuate Conuenticles or exerciſes of Religion by the
Lawes of this Realme prohibited: but to conforme my
ſelfe in all things to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the
Church of <hi>England,</hi> as a member of that Church without
diſturbing the peace and vnitie thereof, and doe bleſſe
and praiſe God, that as a member of the ſaid Church I may
freely ioyne with the Parochiall Congregations, where I
ſhall reſide in the hearing of Diuine Seruice ſaid, Gods
word Preached, and in the participation of the holy and
bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper rightly and duly
adminiſtred, and in all other religious duties. For the
due performance whereof I doe here giue my faithfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe:
and that I may ſo doe, I deſire you all here preſent
to ioyne with me in ſaying the Lords prayer; <hi>Our Father
which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:10126:24"/>
            <head>The Seuerall kinds of Myſticall
Wolues breeding in ENGLAND.
(<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <p>YOu haue heard in the generall handling of the Text,<note place="margin">Segnius irritant animes demiſſa per aurem quam quae ſunt oculis commiſſa fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note>
of diſguiſed and palliated Wolues: but becauſe,
as a<note n="c" place="margin">Horat de art Poet.</note> Poet ſaith truely, things heard with the eare,
oftentimes leaue leſſe impreſſion behinde them then
things ſeene with the eye. Therefore I will now endeuour
in the more particular Application of that which hath
beene ſpoken; to ſhew you, or to preſent before your eyes,
ſuch a very Woolfe as our Sauiour ſpeakes of in my Text.
I confeſſe a<note n="c" place="margin">Sebaſt. Munſter lib. 2. de inſul B. yt.</note> learned Writer ſaith, which might ſeeme a
Paradox, <hi>Nulli ſunt Lupi in Anglia,</hi> that wee haue no
Wolues in England: but for the true vnderſtanding of
that Author, we muſt neceſſarily diſtinguiſh of Wolues:
there be naturall Wolues and myſticall Wolues: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
naturall Wolues (and of them he ſpeakes) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth
truely to the world of our Nation, that wee haue
none of them <hi>ordinarily breeding amongst vs:</hi> but concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
myſticall Wolues, it is quite otherwiſe: in that
ſenſe, <hi>multi ſunt Lupi in Anglia,</hi> we haue many Wolues
in England, we haue Popiſh Wolues which haue ſought
by all poſſible meanes both by force and flatterie, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
all to blindneſſe and ſuperſtition againe, as appeares
by th helliſh Gunpowder-plot neuer to be forgotten, in
the yeere 1605. and other deſignes of theirs: wee haue
Arminian Wolues, which make a bridge betweene vs
and Popery, endeuouring in ſome points to reconcile the
Wolues and the Lambes: which the very Heathen<note n="n" place="margin">Horat epod. 15. dum pecor<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus inſeſtus erit, being put for ſemper.</note> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets
being reaſonable men, haue iudged an impoſſible taske:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10126:25"/>
we haue Anabaptiſticall Wolues, which iumpe with the
Arminians in conditionall election vpon foreſeene faith or
workes, in denying the doctrine of reprobation in the
true ſenſe thereof, in maintaining vniuerſall redemption
of all of all ſorts, in maintaining the doctrine of free-will,
in defending and pleading for falling from grace, or the
totall Apoſtacy of Saints, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I would we had not Roſey-croſſe-Wolues
which turne Diuinity into phanſies, &amp; idle ſpeculations of
their own braine eſteeming text-men, or ſuch as endeauour
to keepe to the naturall ſenſe of Scripture (not daring to
make an allegorie in a Text where the ſpirit of God deſires
to be vnderſtood without an allegorie) to bee vulgar Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines,<note place="margin">Vulgares theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos.</note>
as they inculcate in ſome of their phanſifull bookes;
boaſting alſo of their ability to worke ſuch miracles as I
ſhould tremble to name: but becauſe they doe this more
priuately; being either aſhamed, or affraid it ſhould come
to light, I paſſe it by for the preſent; there may be further
occaſion heereafter giuen vnto ſome to lay them open, that
others may beware of them: Laſtly, I would wee had not
Familiſticall Wolues, and that of diuers ſorts, as firſt, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts
of the Caſtalian order which diſſent from our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
and oppoſe it in euery ſyllable thereof, and yet like
notorious Hypocrites, if they be neuer ſo little queſtioned,
will make ſhew by outward ſeeming conformity, as
though they did highly approue the doctrine of our
Church, and were ready-preſt to defend the ſame: which
hold alſo that the Law of God may bee perfectly fulfilled
by men in this world, which tearme themſelues Eagles,
Angels, and Arch-angels: which hope in a ſhort time to
be inſpired with light and illumination, as farre as euer
<hi>Paul</hi> or any of the Prophets were: which allegorize the
places of Scripture concerning Chriſt, dreaming onely of a
ſactifying Chriſt, and abhorring a iuſtifying Sauiour; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
ſaluation indeed by their own works: holding that
Turkes &amp; Pagans may be ſaued as well as any other if they
liue well, though they had neuer heard of Chriſt: if their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10126:25"/>
be any of this faction ſtill remaining, I wiſh them ſpeedily
to repent, for otherwiſe God no doubt will in time diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
them, notwithſtanding all their ſhifts and hypocriſies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I would we had not Gringltonian Familiſts
in the North parts <hi>of</hi> England, which hold:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Scripture is but for nouices.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the Sabbath is to bee obſerued but as a
Lecture day.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that to pray for pardon of ſinne, after one is
aſſured of Gods loue, is to offer Chriſt againe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that their ſpirit is not to bee tryed by the
Scripture, but the Scripture by their ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that we muſt not now goe by motiues but by
motions.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, that when God comes to dwell in a man, he ſo
fills the ſoule, that there is no more luſting.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, that they ſee no reaſon why Miniſters ſhould
ſpeake againſt the ſinnes of the wicked, ſeeing the
wicked man canne doe nothing but ſinne.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, which boaſt and thanke God, that they haue
caſt off praying in their Families, repeating of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
and ſuch like long agoe.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, which ſcoffe at ſuch as make Conſcience of
words, with many other pernitious points.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I would wee had not Familiſts in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,
which ſay, that they haue quite vanquiſhed the
diuel, that they are pure from all ſinne, and that they
are neuer ſo much as tempted to doubt of their ſpirituall
eſtate. Fourthly, I would we had not Familiſts of the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes
which bring in their damnable doctrine with faire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences
of weeping, of ſighing, of lifting vp the eyes to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
of patience, of a ſmooth carryage and the like. I
would we had not Familiſts of the ſcattered flocke, which
ſeduce by pretending themſelues to bee of them which
feare the Lord when they are nothing leſſe. I would wee
had not Familiſts of Caps his order and of other rankes:
but amongſt the reſt of theſe myſticall Wolues, there
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10126:26"/>
hath beene diſcouered of late to his Maieſties High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion-Court,
a notable cloſe-deuouring Woolfe, one
<hi>Iohn Hetherington</hi> a Boxe-maker, whom I may iuſtly
tearme a Woolfe (according to the title giuen to ſeducers
in my Text) in reſpect of his pernitious doctrine, being
the Teacher to a great number of Factious perſons about
this City: and he may fitly be compared to the Woolfe
<hi>Glanos,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ariſtol. lib. 8. de Hiſt. animal. c. 5.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſeekes to prey vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
men: or to the Woolfe Circus, which in the cold time,
when the Mountaines are couered with ſnow, will impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
enter into the very City to ſeeke for his prey, as
<note n="e" place="margin">In vrbem per famem impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimus accedit.</note> 
               <hi>Geſner</hi> recordeth: euen ſo this myſticall Woolfe vſeth
to prey vpon men, as appeares by the multitude of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall
perſons whom he hath ſeduced; yea, he is growne
ſo impudent, that he is entred into this famous City, to
ceaze vpon his prey there, although he know there be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant
Paſtors in it, able to reſiſt him.</p>
            <p>But that I may proceed methodically in that which I
haue further to write, I will confine the remainder to
three heads: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Matter of Diſcouerie.</item>
               <item>2. Matter of Confutation.</item>
               <item>3. Matter of Admonition.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Concerning Matter of Diſcouerie; I confeſſe I haue an
hard taske, for who ſhall make men beleeue they ſee a
Woolfe, when outwardly in the skinne, there appeares
onely the reſemblance of a ſilly innocent ſheepe: but I
hope I haue to deale with a prudent age of men (<hi>qui ex
vngue Leonem</hi>) which haue learned to know a Lyon, if
they ſee but one of his pawes: now I will endeuour to
diſcouer this cloſe Sectary foure waies:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By the Oathes of honeſt Witneſſes.</item>
               <item>2. By his owne erroneous Bookes.</item>
               <item>3. By comparing him with antient Heretickes.</item>
               <item>4. By applying vnto him the words of my Text.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="discovery">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:10126:26"/>
               <head>The firſt Diſcouery of Iohn Hetherington,
which is by the oathes is honest
Witneſſes.</head>
               <p>This man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> being metamorpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
or changed from a man to a Woolfe, as<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 8. de repub.</note> 
                  <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeakes
of a Tyrant, was diſcouered to the forenamed Honourable
Court, and teſtified againſt vpon the oathes, not of Knights
of the Poſt, but of many honeſt conſcionable men, againſt
whoſe perſons or ſayings, <hi>Hetherington</hi> himſelfe the party
defendant did propound no manner of exceptions; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
hee had ſufficient time allowed him by the
Court, nor euer ſo much as offered to except againſt them
in any Legall courſe: by the teſtimonies of theſe vntainted
Witneſſes, which were not a few, and whereof two were
Miniſters of good note, it appeared and was proued.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the ſaid <hi>Hetherington</hi> hauing beene by trade
a Boxe-maker, caſt off his trade, and betooke himſelfe to
be an interpreter of the Scripture to many perſons, not of
his owne Family, keeping priuate Conuenticles by the
Lawes of this Realme prohibited, in the which Conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles:
hee tooke vpon him to bee the chiefe ſpeaker, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor
in points of doctrine, and matters of Faith, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
many interpretations contrary to the receiued Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets
taught and held in the Church of England.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that he hath maintained and publiſhed, that
the Church of England is no true Church of Chriſt; that
it teacheth falſe doctrine, hauing vſed alſo many reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
ſpeeches to, and of the Reuerend Miniſters of our
Church, whereby hee hath withdrawne many from the
Church of England to his owne Faction.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that he is a man diſaffected to the gouernement
and diſcipline of the Church of England now by law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
and agreeth in opinion with the Sect of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10126:27"/>
and other Sectaries: holding with the Familiſts
the perfect purity of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that ſince the twentieth of <hi>December,</hi> 1623.
hee hath maintained, and publiſhed, that the Sabbath
ſince the Apoſtles time was of no force; and that euery
day is a Sabbath, as much as that which we call the Lords
day, or Sonday.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, that he holdeth and maintaineth, that the books
of <hi>Eſdras</hi> are part of the Canonicall Scripture, and that
they ought ſo to be eſteemed.</p>
               <p>For the which his erroneous opinions and Schiſmaticall
carriage tending to the diſturbance of the peace of the
Church, and to the ſeducing of many ſillie ſoules, the
Court adiudged him to be a dangerous Sectary, and one
that was well worthy to bee reſtrained and puniſhed, and
amongſt the reſt of the puniſhments laid vpon him, this
was one; that hee ſhould publikely recant his errors at
<hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe; wherein the ſentence of that Honourable
Court, is like to the cenſure of the Church vpon Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes
in the daies of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in the which time, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares
by<note n="c" place="margin">Epiſt. Athanaſ. ad Antioch.</note> one of his Epiſtles, if any did fall or reuolt from
the Church to Arianiſme, and afterwards repenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
of his reuolt deſired to be reconciled to the Church
againe, amongſt the reſt of his puniſhments, enioyned him
by the Church for his Apoſtacle, this was one: that hee
ſhould publikely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce,
or make a Recantation of his Arian hereſie. For
this worthy Sentence, all Gods ſeruants in this City,
haue great cauſe to glorifie God; yea, I hope alſo his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty
will take ſpeciall notice of it for the encouragement
of his worthy Commiſſioners in wel-doing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="discovery">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:10126:27"/>
               <head>The ſecond Diſcouerie of Iohn Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,
which is by his
Bookes.</head>
               <p>Come we now to the ſecond Diſcouerie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> Bookes put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coueries, becauſe they are vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> which is by
his Bookes. The ſaid <hi>Hetherington</hi> and his Factious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
haue certaine Bookes wherewith they doe vſually
ſeduce and withdraw men and women from the Church
of England: and theſe ſeducing Bookes are of two ſorts,
either ſuch as were made by <hi>Hetherington</hi> himſelfe (for it
is true which <hi>Horace</hi> ſaith, <hi>ſcribimus indocti doctique poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata
paſſim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hodiè quidam omnium bonaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> literarum prorſus rudes &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> pauculis ſophiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus vt malè deguflata Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoletis philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia freti pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ac manibus illotis irruant in theolagia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſionem. Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus de vita Hieronymi.</note> ignorant idiots in our daies will bee writing
Bookes as well as the Learned) or ſuch as were made by
his predeceſſor, <hi>T. L.</hi> who was as it ſeemes the ringlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of this factious company before <hi>Hetherington:</hi> for let
vs take notice of this, for certainety that when any Sectma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
dies, or leaueth a place, either amongſt Anabaptiſts,
or Familiſts, another ordinarily ſucceeds him in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
to vphold the faction.</p>
               <p>The firſt Booke written by <hi>Hetherington</hi> himſelfe, is
that againſt one <hi>Smith</hi> an Anabaptiſt, wherein vnder a
colour of writing againſt Anabaptiſts, he broacheth (but
very cunningly) his owne familiſticall errors.</p>
               <p>In this Booke againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> printed in the yeere, 1610.
he cunningly coucheth many dangerous errors: to name
but ſome of them for breuity ſake.</p>
               <p>At page 1. he acknowledgeth no other Church but that
which conſiſts of liuing ſtones, meaning by his Church of
liuing ſtones, his owne factious Company, as all Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes
vnderſtand none but themſelues, whenſoeuer they
ſpeake of the true Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, vnto this fanſied Church he appropriateth the
power of the keyes, page 2. 65. falſly interpreting that in
<hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 17. tell the Church, that is, ſaith he, at page 74.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10126:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
tell it to thoſe little ones borne of God: whereas it is
meant, that we ſhould tell the Gouernours of the Church
which are in place and authority, wether they bee regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
or vnregenerate.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, at page 7. 8. he arrogateth to his Church the
knowledge of infallibility in iudging concerning the
members of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, at page 81. 82. hee ſaith, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> may
command a place in publike, ſo he doe forbid none in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate:
wherein hee ſpeaketh cunningly for the liberty of
Conuenticles, as I thinke any which know him will eaſily
diſcerne.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, at page 86. he ſaith, the Pope hath his power
from God, and that he muſt be obeyed; wherein hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth
his notorious Hypocriſie: as being ready if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
were offered to ſubmit outwardly to Antichriſt
himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, at page 88. 89.<note n="c" place="margin">For mine owne part I will not be peremptory in the interpreting of his meaning, but let wiſe men reade the words and giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> hee ſeemes cunningly to
teach his Proſelytes not to ſcruple at outward circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
if occaſion be offered, nor at ſitting in the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
(hee would ſay poſſibly, if hee durſt, at going to the
Maſſe) abuſing that in 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. 19. where the Prophet
bids <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> goe in peace, as though hee had
bid him goe in peace to the houſe of <hi>Rimmon:</hi> whereby
it may appeare, what this man and his Proſelytes would
doe if Circumciſion were vrged vpon them by the Turke,
or going to the Maſſe by the Pope: and indeed ſome of
his Proſelytes haue beene obſerued to ſay, that if hee
were at <hi>Rome</hi> hee would ioyne with them there aſſoone
as with vs heere: many other pernitious errors are
couched in this Booke againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> by cunning intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
which none ſhall ordinarily vnderſtand (though they
reade the Booke) but onely his ſeduced Proſelytes, which
are ſecretly acquainted with his myſtery: it is obſerued
by<note n="c" place="margin">In prompt, con. 2. c. 8. dux peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pateticorum ſe ea lege, ſua natura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lia inſtituta tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didiſſe dixit vt nemo intelligeret, niſi ipſo qui tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit inter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tante.</note> 
                  <hi>Franciſcus Venetus</hi> a very learned Writer concerning
<hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that he wrote his naturall Philoſophy with that
art, that none ſhould vnderſtand the precepts thereof, ſaue
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10126:28"/>
onely they which were his Schollers, and vnto whom hee
himſelfe would vouchſafe to interpret them. <hi>Iohn Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi>
is like <hi>Aristotle</hi> in this reſpect, not for learning,
but for cunning: none ſhall fully vnderſtand all his errors
but ſuch idiots as are his Proſelytes.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Booke written by <hi>Hetherington</hi> (as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
ſaith) is that which was ſet forth in the name of one
<hi>Edmund Ieſop,</hi> called the diſcouery of the errors of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts.
Wherein by the way) <hi>Ieſop</hi> deſerues no ſmall
rebuke, for whereas at that time he made a ſhew of tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
from the Anabaptiſts to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> hee
turned not to vs but to <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> faction, and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
with him about the making of this erroneous Booke;
howbeit by his hypocriticall ſeeming to turne, he reaped
no ſmall gaine to himſelfe, as it is well knowne. But to
let him paſſe, and to come to the errors of the Booke.</p>
               <p>In this Booke at page 3. he confoundeth Reprobation
and Damnation, making the foreſight of mans folly and
wickedneſſe to be the cauſe why God preordaines any to
condemnation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, at page 18. hee affirmeth that the Goſpell
hath bin declared to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in former times, and is
declared at this preſent in diuers parts of the world, onely
by the workes of creation, wherein he teacheth cunningly
that pernicious point,<note n="c" place="margin">Nota eſt Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</note> expreſly maintained by him and his
followers in their priuate Conuenticles, <hi>viz.</hi> that a man
may be ſaued without Chriſt reuealed in the word, by the
meere contemplation of the creatures: abuſing that in
<hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 18. which ſpeakes of ſuch a preaching by the
creatures which leaues men without excuſe, not which is
ſufficient to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, at Page 48. hee cunningly coucheth a point
which is maintained by him and his factious company; to
wit, that the ſoule of man comes <hi>ex traduce,</hi> that is, that
it is traduced from <hi>Adam</hi> as well as the body, and that it
is not immediately infuſed of God into this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:10126:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Fourthly, at Page 61 he ſpeaketh diſhonorably of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme;
for hee ſaith, <hi>What can men haue leſſe then Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,
which can giue to no man more then an outward
name of a Chriſtian, as Circumciſion did the outward
name of a Iew, it doth neither conferre nor confirme grace
to the heart of any, no more then Circumciſion did.</hi> And
in his former Booke at pag. 13. hee ſpeaketh contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
of Baptiſme, tearming it elementiſh baptiſme. And
indeede it is apparant to them which know and are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted
with his opinions, that hee holds no other Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
to be of any vertue, but that which he cals the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing
in a thouſand teares, in his former Booke at page
14. allegorizing the Sacrament, as the reſt of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts
doe. And herein appeares the hypocriſie of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
they will ſubmit to vſe our Sacraments, and to
come to our Churches, and yet haue them in plaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, whereas at page 89. he condemnes the Familiſts
of <hi>H. N.</hi> his order as the moſt blaſphemous and errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
Sect this day in the world. I anſwer, all this he may
doe and yet remaine a notorious Familiſt himſelfe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
order: for as it is amongſt the Anabaptiſts, ſo it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
amongſt the Familiſts: there be diuers orders of them,
and they doe mutually hate and oppoſe one another. The
Familiſts of the <hi>Castalion</hi> order deſpiſe them of Caps
his order, accounting them ſimple men; and they of <hi>Caps</hi>
his order fauour not them of <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> order,
and they of <hi>Hertheringtons</hi> order gnaſh their teeth againſt
all but their owne faction.</p>
               <p>Sixty, at pag. 101. he deliuers a ſtrange paradox, <hi>viz.</hi>
that Sathan himſelfe with all his Angels and ſpirits of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe,
by force of their torments ſhall be compelled
with all powers, people and kings whatſoeuer, to confeſſe
&amp; bow before Chriſt, to ſerue and obey him, to praiſe and
magnifie him, his Iuſtice and Mercy for euer, abuſing that
place in <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 10, 11. which proues not that euer hell
ſhall be made a Chappell to praiſe God in. Thus fooliſh
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10126:29"/>
and ignorant men will take vpon them to be teachers of
Diuinitie, being vnſeene in the very grounds thereof: much
like to preſumptuous Quackſaluers,<note place="margin">Verum penitus abſurdum eſt vt diſcipulus ad magiſtrum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, antè ſit ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſex quam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceatur, Hier. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Luciferian.</note> which take vpon
them to be great Chirurgians and Phyſicians, being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded
in the art of Surgerie and Phyſicke: and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
of curing men, doe indeede kill them.</p>
               <p>There be moreouer other Books whereby this Sect doe
ſeduce, written by <hi>T. L. Hetheringtons</hi> predeceſſor; to
wit, Firſt, the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Secondly,
the tree of regeneration. Thirdly, an Expoſition vpon the
11, 12, 13. Chapters of the <hi>Reuelation.</hi> Fourthly, the Key of
<hi>Dauid,</hi> and ſome other.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Epiſtle pretended to be written to the
Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is ſaid in the Preface of it; that this
Booke deſerueth as well to be regarded, as the beſt newes
that euer thou haſt heard: now the beſt newes that euer
we haue heard as we know is the Goſpell; and I appeale
to the conſciences of this factious company, whether they
haue not in contempt all writings ſince the Apoſtles time
in compariſon of <hi>T. L.</hi> his writings; yea, whether they
doe not equalize them to the very Scripture it ſelfe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting
<hi>T. L.</hi> a great Prophet.</p>
               <p>In this Booke of his, at page 16. the Author ſolemnly
proteſteth that hee knew not any one after the fleſh that
taketh part with him, wherein hee ſheweth himſelfe a
notorious factioniſt, in thinking himſelfe alone, in the
dayes of the libertie of the Goſpell. Secondly, although
this railing Epiſtle be pretended onely to be written to
the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet it is intended alſo againſt our
Church, as it doth manifeſtly appeare by his girding at
Huſſites, Lutherans, Caluiniſts, Euangeliſts, Proteſtants,
and Preciſians, at pag. 108. and by his girding at falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
Prophets at page 69. wherein hee cunningly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigheth
againſt all reformed Churches whom he tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
in the tree of regeneration, at pag. 20. fooliſh and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hetherington</hi> and his company are well knowne to deſpiſe all Churches in the world reformed and vnreformed, and to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted Church but their owne faction.</note> reformers. Thirdly, in this Epiſtle to the
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> at pag. 113. The Author ſaith when hee
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10126:30"/>
wrote this Epiſtle, that he was in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and yet he liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in <hi>England</hi> in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, yea hee was ſo
impudent, as to dedicate one of his Bookes to that Queene
of famous memory, expreſſing his name onely by two let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<hi>T. L.</hi> leſt the Purſeuant ſhould finde him out. I thinke
I doe not gueſſe amiſſe at his meaning: and what was this,
but to call our Church <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the very times of the
Goſpell. Fourthly, at pag. 86. hee ſaith come forth yee
theeues and murderers out of your dennes and palaces: if
he were now aliue, I would demand of him whom hee
meanes by his theeues and murderers in palaces.</p>
               <p>As for his ſecond Booke called the Tree of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
the ſcope of it is as his aime is in the reſt of his Bookes.
Firſt, to intimate himſelfe to be a Prophet, at pag. 2. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
to reuile the publike meetings of the Church or
the Congregations, and by this meanes to withdraw men
from them, at pag. 18. 19. Thirdly, to reproach the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
which come to preferment in the Church by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
of Princes, tearming them the Sonnes of <hi>Beor,</hi> at
pag. 26. Fourthly, cunningly to gird at the prerogatiue
of Kings, with the which hee ſaith, ſome are drunken:
at pag. 23.</p>
               <p>I will not further inſiſt vpon any more of his Bookes,
but conſidering how many haue bin already ſeduced by
them; hundreds by report, I cannot doe leſſe then wiſh
(tendring the ſafetie of the Church) that they were deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
to the fire, like thoſe bookes of witchcraft or of curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
arts ſpoken of in <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 19.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="discovery">
               <head>The third Diſcouerie of Iohn Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,
which is by comparing
him with antient Sectaries.</head>
               <p>I finde by that which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath concerning
ancient Heretickes or Sectaries,<note place="margin">Lib de Hareſ.</note> that <hi>Hetherington</hi> agreeth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10126:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in opinion with diuers of them: as Firſt, with the Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes
in an high conceit of his owne knowledge, for as
they did glory in that name, as though they had beene the
onely Ginoskites or knowing men in the world, euen ſo
this man is the <hi>Elias</hi> left alone, the Miniſters of England in
compariſon of him are blinde guides, not able to interpret
one place of Scripture aright, if wee may beleeue his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes
which ſo boaſt of him, as was depoſed againſt ſome
of them in Court, or his owne practice in taking vpon him
(as was alſo proued) to deliuer in his Conuenticles many
contrary things to the receiued opinions in the Church of
England, oppoſing his owne priuate conceits againſt the
iudgement of the whole Church.</p>
               <p>Secondly, with the Cathariſts and Iouinianiſts which
held, that a man cannot ſin (<hi>Lauacro regenerationis accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>)
after he bee once Regenerated, euen ſo this man holds
the perfect purity of the ſoule as was prooued againſt
him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, with the Manicheans, which held <hi>baptiſmu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
in aqua nihil cuiquam ſalutis afferre,</hi> euen ſo this man
holds, that Baptiſme neither confers, nor confirmes grace
to the heart of any as hath beene demonſtrated before out
of his booke, ſet out in the name of <hi>Ieſop</hi> one of his factious
Proſelytes, at page 61.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, with the Mathematici, which receiued the
Apocrypha as well as the Canonicall Scripture, but allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized
and peruerted both for their owne turnes, euen ſo
this man makes ſhew to receiue the Scripture, yea, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
alſo ſome of the Apocrypha for Canonicall, as hath
been prooued againſt him: but how he peruerteth both for
the maintenance of his owne factious opinions, is manifeſt
in his erroneous bookes or Pamphlets.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, with the Vadiani <hi>culpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes epiſcopos diuites,</hi> ſaue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
that he &amp; his factious company are more cenſorious then
they: for they onely blamed rich Biſhops, enuying their
proſperity, but theſe both Biſhops and Curates, affirming
as hath beene depoſed againſt them, that Biſhops and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10126:31"/>
as they are conſecrated in the Church of England,
are not ſo much as members of the Church.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, with the Elceſeitae, which held <hi>fidem in perſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione
eſſe negandam &amp; in corde ſeruandam,</hi> that a man, if he
were perſecuted for his Faith, might lawfully denie it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
that hee kept it ſtill in his heart: and doth not the
Hetherigtonian faction agree vnto this? Did not <hi>Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi>
call God to witneſſe, that he was ſree from ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions
as were laid to his charge. I wiſh him to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
what he hath written, or ſaid to this purpoſe, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
his letter which he wrote to a great man in this
Kingdome for his enlargement: indeed it is true, he will
ſeeme to maintaine ſome of his erroneous opinions to this
day, but I wiſh for his own good, that it were not rather to
inrich himſelfe in the Priſon by drawing mony from his
numerous multitude of Proſelytes, as ſome other beſides
himſelfe haue beene knowne to doe. then for any conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
he makes of denying what he holds: I might compare
this man with many other Sectaries, mentioned by <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,
Euſebius, Epiphanius,</hi> and other Fathers which write
of Heretickes: but I ſtudy breuity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="discovery">
               <head>The fourth Diſcouery of Iohn Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,
which is by the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
of the Text.</head>
               <p>In the laſt place, this man may be much diſcouered by
the right Application of my Text. For firſt he is a Woolfe
in the ſenſe of my Text. Secondly, hee comes in ſheepes
cloathing: that he is a Woolfe in the ſenſe of my Text, is
manifeſt to all that know him <hi>intus &amp; in cute:</hi> for Firſt,
he deales gently with his Proſelytes at the firſt drawing
them into lighter errors (although I muſt needs ſay, I
know no one error that he holds which is ſimply light) but
afterwards like a rauening Woolfe, he teares their ſoules in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10126:31"/>
pieces by bringing them by his ſpirituall inchantments, to
deſpiſe the Church, to reiect the publicke Miniſtery, or at
the leaſt to ceaſſe to eſteeme and beleeue it, to haue the
Lords Day in contempt, to caſt off holy duties in priuate
Families and the like; all this is very well knowne in the
Citie, to ſuch as doe but know his followers.</p>
               <p>Secondly, hee is very dull to vnderſtand the truth, for
who is more blockiſh then he which is ignorant, and yet
ſcornes to be taught: but he is very quick-ſighted to finde
out cunning euaſions and ſubtill equiuocations to hide his
pernitious errors if poſſibly he may from the eye of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
this I am perſwaded prudent men before whom he
hath been conuented, doe partly diſcerne, beſides others
which haue conuerſed with him and his factious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, as a Woolfe begets a Woolfe, ſo this ſectary
where he preuailes with any man or woman, to make
them his Proſelytes, hee makes them like vnto himſelfe:
will he equiuocate? ſo will they: will hee traduce good
Miniſters and good people terming them puritans
though they be conformable? ſo will they: will he ſeeke
to ſeduce? ſo will they: I may well ſpeake this by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
conſidering that many tender-conſcienced Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
in my Pariſh haue beene tampered with by theſe ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
fellowes, and ſollicited to <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> Conuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles:
wherefore, as it was once feined concerning <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that hee begat new Gods as<note n="c" place="margin">Eurip in <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> one of the
Greeke Poets hath it. So it may bee ſaid concerning <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therington</hi>
without fiction, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, he begets
new Proſelytes, which quickly turne traducers of the
Church, if not worſe then ſo.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he comes in ſheepes cloathing: for Firſt hee
comes with quotations of Scripture to maintaine pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
errors, witneſſe his bookes. Secondly, he comes with
flattering words, pretending to tender mens ſoules and
the like; witneſſe many which haue beene aſſaulted by
him or by his followers. Thirdly, he comes with lincy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woolſie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10126:32"/>
bookes, ſuch as ſauour of ſome ſeeming deuotion,
but conteining dangerous errors cloſely couched. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
he comes in the whole outſide of a Chriſtian; there is
nothing a true Chriſtian hath indeed, but theſe fellowes
to ſerue their owne turne can haue it in ſhew, they can ſigh,
and weepe &amp; humble themſelues, and make ſhew of ſome
ciuill vertues, &amp;c. but all this is ioyned with pernitious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
of iudgement and ſchiſme. Fifthly, he hath his ſheepes
cloathing alſo, wherewith to deceiue authority, <hi>viz.</hi> his
falſe recriminations, his feined ſubmiſſions, his hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
equiuocations, his ſhameleſſe denyals, with many ſuch:
if any ſhall deſire to be further ſatisfied concerning <hi>Hethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi>
and his factious company, let him but enquire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
honeſt Religious Citizens, and hee ſhall not onely
finde this little which I ſay true of them, but much
more.</p>
               <p>And thus I haue endeuoured to ſhew you this Woolfe
in his owne skinne. I pray God diſcouer him further for the
ſafety of his Church: and thus alſo I haue done with the
firſt thing propounded; namely, the Diſcouerie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
howſoeuer I may ſeeme to vſe ſharpneſſe in Zeale for
the Church, yet I am ſure I haue mingled no malice, for I
neuer had any particular quarrell againſt him in all my life
as he well knoweth: &amp; hauing diſpatched the Diſcouerie,
it remaineth now according to our Method propounded,
that we come to matter of Confutation; and heerein I doe
not meane to inſiſt vpon the refutation of euery dotage
which he is knowne to hold, for ſo I might bee infinite. I
will not ſtand to proue againſt him, that the Church of
England is a true Church, for this were to hold a candle
to ſee the Sunne by, which is ſeene ſufficiently by its owne
light: a chaſte Spouſe remaineth an honeſt woman, though
neuer ſo many varlots reproach her as an harlot, euen ſo
the Church of England, my deare Mother ſhall remaine I
hope for the future, and is for the preſent a true Church,
when all peeuiſh Schiſmatickes, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts,
Familiſts and ſuch like, haue ſaid or rayled what they can
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10126:32"/>
againſt her: neither wil I inſiſt vpon his dotage concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the perfect purity of the ſoule: that in 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>If
we ſay we haue not ſinne, we deceiue our ſelues:</hi> is ſufficient
to confound whatſoeuer hee or his Proſelytes are able to
produce to the contrary.</p>
               <p>But that which we will
ſtand vpon ſhall be
<list>
                     <item>1. The Sabbath.</item>
                     <item>2. The Bookes of <hi>Eſdras.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Sabbath day, or that which we call the Lords day,
is no more a Sabbath in <hi>Hetheringtons</hi> opinion then any
other day, as was proued by the oathes of honeſt men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him: wherein like vnto <hi>Faux,</hi> he would blow vp
all Religion at one blaſt by the Gun-powder of Familiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
Doctrine, and open a window to all Atheiſme and
prophanneſſe: for take away the Sabbath, and farrewell
all Religion: neither let this equiuocator ſay, that he doth
not vtterly denie the morality of the Sabbath, but onely
that hee holds it is not to be ſo ſtrictly kept as it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the Iewes, &amp;c. for it is perfectly knowne to many
in the City, which I hope may eaſily be produced if need
ſhould require, that neither <hi>Hetherington</hi> nor his followers
make any conſcience of working in their ordinary trades
vpon that day, or of buying and ſelling and the like: yea,
the truth is, as appeares by ſome that haue beene intimate
with them, and by ſome other that haue beene conuerted
from them, that where their pernicious doctrine doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile,
it brings men or women to a plaine contempt of the
Sabbath, to worke vpon that day to deſpight others, yea,
to<note n="c" place="margin">Tearming them ſuperſtitious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> nickname others which make conſcience to keepe it
as was alſo depoſed againſt them: to come therefore to
that which this dangerous Sectary maketh a controuerſie,
<hi>viz.</hi> to proue the Morality of the Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:10126:33"/>
               <head>The Morality of the Sabbath proued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Sect of the Familiſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
Hetherington and other
Antiſabbatareans.</head>
               <p>THe true Morality of the Sabbath conſiſting not in a
myſticall reſting from ſinne as the Familiſts pretend,
but in celebrating of an appointed day in ſeuen in the
worſhip and ſeruice of God, may bee demonſtrated and
proued by the arguments following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from the time when it was firſt inſtituted and
celebrated and that was in the time of mans innocency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
any Moſaicall Ceremonie was in vſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 3. indeed
in the ſtate of innocency, God had giuen vnto <hi>Adam</hi> the
Law concerning the Tree of knowledge of good and euill,
yet that tree was no Moſaicall Ceremonie, but a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from the manner of writing of the fourth
Commandement at the firſt, for it was not written in
paper or parchment, or vpon leaues of trees, but in
Tables of ſtone, as the reſt of the tenne Commadements
were, <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> 10. 1. to ſignifie the perpetuity
thereof.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, from Gods owne placing of it: for the Law
of the Sabbath, to wit, the fourth Commandement is not
placed amongſt the Ceremoniall or Iudiciall Lawes, as
though it had beene Ceremoniall, or had concerned onely
the Nation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or them eſpecially: but amongſt
the Morall Lawes, yea it is made one of the ten, ſo that if
it were abrogated, there would remaine but nine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
and ſo the Law of God were vnperfect,
which were blaſphemie to affirme: neither let Familiſts
thinke to euade by ſaying the moralitie of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
ſtill remaineth in reſting from ſinne euery
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10126:33"/>
day; for the moralitie of that Commandement conſiſteth
not in that, but in celebrating one day of ſeauen in Gods
ſeruice, as we noted before, and as may appeare by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
words of the Commandement preſſing onely the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
of a ſeauenth day.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, from the reaſons wherewith the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
is inforced, which are all of them morall, and
doe as ſtrongly binde the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as the <hi>Iewes:</hi> for if the
<hi>Iewes</hi> were bound in conſcience to celebrate the ſeauenth
day in Gods ſeruice to his glory, becauſe the Lord had
giuen them ſix dayes for their owne lawfull occaſions, are
not we <hi>Gentiles</hi> by the ſame reaſon bound, vnto whom
God in like manner hath granted ſix dayes for our owne
labours requiring but the ſeauenth for his publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.
Secondly, if the <hi>Iewes</hi> were bound to celebrate the
ſeauenth day, becauſe it was the Lords due, or becauſe it
was <hi>the Sabbath of the Lord thy God:</hi> are not the <hi>Gentiles</hi>
bound in like manner to giue God his right. Thirdly, ſhall
the example of God in reſting vpon the ſeauenth day from
all his workes of Creation binde the <hi>Iewes</hi> and not vs
<hi>Gentiles?</hi> are not wee bound to be imitators of God as
deare children, as well as they, or any other? <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. 1.
Fourthly, ſhall it be an argument to perſwade the <hi>Iewes</hi> to
keepe the Sabbath, becauſe God hath bleſſed and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
it; that is, hath ordained it to be a day of bleſſing to
the conſcionable obſeruers of it, and hath ſet it apart from
common labour to holy vſe? and ſhall it not be an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to perſwade vs? haue not we as much neede of Gods
bleſſing as the <hi>Iewes?</hi> haue not wee cauſe to feare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure
that which is ſanctified as well as the <hi>Iewes?</hi> Thus
we ſee all the reaſons in the fourth Commandement are
morall, which doe plainly demonſtrate the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
it ſelfe to be morall.</p>
               <p>Now if any ſhall obiect that in <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 15. where God
preſſeth the obſeruation of the Sabbath, with a reaſon ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
to be peculiar to the <hi>Hebrewes;</hi> namely, becauſe he
had brought them out of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> I anſwer, that doth no
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10126:34"/>
more infringe the moralitie of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
then the generall Praeface praefixed before the ten
Commandements, <hi>I am the Lord thy God, which brought
thee out of the land of Aegypt, and out of the houſe of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,</hi>
doth infringe the moralitie of the reſt of the morall
Law. Secondly, there was ſomething alſo ſignified in this
reaſon, <hi>I brought thee out of the land of Aegypt;</hi> to wit, the
great benefit of redemption, which bindes the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as
well as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> in way of thankfulneſſe to celebrate the
Sabbath day to Gods glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Reaſons prouing againſt Hetherington and
other Familists, that the Lords day
ought to be kept for the
Chriſtian Sabbath.</head>
               <p>THat the Lords day ought to be celebrated for the
Chriſtians Sabbath; and that by vertue of the mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
of the fourth Commandement: it is apparent by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
Arguments.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the morall Law is not abrogated by the
Goſpell, but eſtabliſhed, <hi>Rom</hi> 3. 31. which proues that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net
of <hi>Hetherington</hi> to be falſe; to wit, that the Lords day
ſince the Apoſtles time was of no force.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe it is written in the very hearts of men,
that they ought to celebrate that day, as appeares by the
ſecret checkes that they finde in their conſciences when
they doe prophane it, and by the ſweet comforts which
they feele when they keepe it in an holy manner,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this bleſſed day hath bin obſerued by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Churches: it was kept at <hi>Hieruſalem, Act.</hi> 2. 1. it was
kept at <hi>Troas Act.</hi> 20. 7. it was kept in <hi>Patmos, Reuel.</hi> 1.
10. it was kept in the regions of <hi>Galatia,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 16. 1. 2.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the ancient Fathers haue preſſed the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Lords day vpon the Church in their ſeuerall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.
<note n="c" place="margin">Epiſt. ad mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſi<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> 
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaith, let euery one which loueth Chriſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10126:34"/>
celebrate the Lords day,<note n="e" place="margin">Ser. 251. de tempor.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth greatly
preſſe the ſtrict obſeruation of the Lords day that men
ſhould vpon that day be ſeparated from worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
and that they ſhould attend vpon Gods publike
worſhip: that they ſhould not ſit idling at home when
others goe to Church; that they ſhould not giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
to hunting vpon that day, or to loud laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
&amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">In 1. cap. Iſaiae.</note> Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, when as almoſt all dayes preſcribed
by the Law are aboliſhed, yet there remaineth one great
day of the Lord which ſhall neuer be aboliſhed, but ſhall
remaine to the end of the world.<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. 7. de diuin. offic.</note> 
                  <hi>Rupertus</hi> ſaith, the
Lord hath made this day to be the ſolemnitie of Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities,
becauſe the nobleneſſe of this ſolemnitie excelleth
all other ſolemnities.<note n="g" place="margin">Lib. 4. aduerſ. Marcion.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt hath
made the Sabbath more holy by his benefaction, it being
holy from the beginning by his fathers benediction.<note n="i" place="margin">Hom. 7. in 15. c. exod.</note> Saint
<hi>Origen</hi> doth in like manner not onely equalize, but alſo
farre preferre the Chriſtians Lords day before the <hi>Iewes</hi>
Sabbath.<note n="n" place="margin">Enchir.</note> 
                  <hi>Luther</hi> bleſſeth God for ſetting apart a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
day for the vſe of his ordinances: yea<note n="o" place="margin">Lib. 2. inſtit. c. 8. Sect. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Caluin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
ſaith, vnleſſe a certaine time were ſet apart for the
worſhip of God, all would runne to ruine and confuſion
ſpeedily and ineuitably. Here I am, as the learned know, in
a large field, I might be very copious in quotations, both
out of the ancient Fathers and moderne writers, but I muſt
be briefe for diuers reaſons.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, the<note n="r" place="margin">Homilie of the place and time of prayer.</note> Church of <hi>England</hi> hath theſe words in one
of the Homilies; <hi>God hath giuen expreſſe charge to all men
that vpon the Sabbath day, which is now our Sunday, they
ceaſe from all weekely and work-day labour, to the intent
that like as God himſelfe wrought ſix dayes and rested the
ſeauenth, and bleſſed and ſanctified it; and conſecrated it to
quietneſſe and reſt from labour; euen ſo Gods obedient peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
ſhould vſe the Sunday holily, and reſt from their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
and daily buſineſſe, and alſo giue themſelues wholly to
heauenly exerciſes of Gods true religion and ſeruice. So that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:10126:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
God doth not onely command the obſeruation of this holy day,
but alſo by his owne example doth ſtirre and prouoke to dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
keeping of the ſame.</hi> The which I haue noted, firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the <hi>Hetheringtonians</hi> hold, as it is well knowne, that
the Chriſtians Sabbath is grounded vpon no precept in all
Gods word, whereas the Homily ſaith that God hath
commanded the obſeruation of this holy day. Secondly,
becauſe ſome not well affected would cry downe all
ſtricktneſſe in obſeruing this day as <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> wherein they
doe not ſymphonize with their mother; for what obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Sabbath can be more holily ſtrict, then that
which is preſcribed in the Homily; to wit, that we ſhould
ceaſe from all weekely labour, and giue our ſelues wholly
to heauenly exerciſes of Gods true religion and ſeruice.
We are prone by corruption of nature to take libertie of
our ſelues,<note place="margin">Si non ſatis inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iat inſtiges eum apud Terent.</note> we neede not be taught it: <hi>non opus eſt calcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
ſed frano.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, God hath ſhewed fearfull iudgements vpon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners
of the Lords day, as you may read in the <hi>Practice of
Pietie:</hi> a certaine husbandman grinding Corne vpon the
Lords day, had all his meale burned to aſhes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> another car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying
Corne vpon the ſame day, had his Barne and all his
Corne the next night burned. A couetous Flaxwoman at
Kingſtat in <hi>France</hi> in the yeere 1559. vſing with her mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
to worke in her trade vpon the Lords day, her flax in
an extraordinary manner tooke fire the ſame day, burnt
her houſe, and ſo ſcorched her ſelfe and two of her children
that they all of them dyed the next day. <hi>Stratford vpon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uon</hi>
was twiſe almoſt conſumed with fire in one yeere; and
the like iudgement was ſhewed vpon <hi>Teuerton</hi> in <hi>Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire:</hi>
both which townes were knowne to ſuffer much
prophanation of the Sabbath. In the yeere 1582. <hi>Ian.</hi> 13.
being the Lords day, the ſcaffolds in Pariſgarden fell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the people at a Bearebaiting, ſo that eight were ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſlaine, and many others hurt and maimed. Alſo a certain
Nobleman vſually prophaning the Sabbath by hunting,
had a childe by his Lady, which had an head like a dogs
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10126:35"/>
head with eares and iawes anſwerable, making alſo a noiſe
when it cried like an Hound. In like manner a woman,
as I am informed, preparing a paire of ſtockings for the
market vpon the Lords day with a pan of coales at <hi>Parſhore</hi>
in the Countie of <hi>Worcester,</hi> her houſe was burnt and two
and twenty more vpon the ſame day. It is certaine there
were ſo many houſes burnt, and that vpon the Lords day,
for that appeares by the Briefe which was gathered at the
Churches. And that the fire came by this meanes, ſome
that then dwelt in the towne, ſaid vnto mee, that they
would be depoſed of the truth of it.</p>
               <p>All which may be faire warnings to forewarne not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
prophaners of the Sabbath, but alſo all ſuch as by their
pernicious doctrine teach men to prophane it.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly, there is infinite neceſſitie of a Lords day or
Sabbath. Firſt, for the reſt of poore Seruants and Cattell,
which otherwiſe might ſinke vnder the burden of vnceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
labour. Secondly, for the ſanctification of euery one
of vs: how worldly minded ſhould the beſt of vs grow,
if we had not the Sabbath to take of our hearts from the
world? Thirdly, for the inſtruction of the ignorant:
what inſtruction haue many thouſands in this Kingdome
and elſewhere, but onely that which they receiue vpon
the Sabbath day. Fourthly, for Gods worſhip and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
ſeruice, when is God publikely worſhipped in the
Countrey ordinarily, but vpon the Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Obiections againſt the Sabbath
anſwered.</head>
               <p>HAuing thus proued the Moralitie of the Sabbath,
come we now to anſwer the Obiections which the
Familiſts and their adherents bring to infringe the ſame.
Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Obiection.</note> you keepe not, ſay they, the ſame day which the
<hi>Iewes</hi> kept, and therefore you grant by your owne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,
that the Law of the Sabbath is not Morall. I anſwer,
they might as truely ſay our practiſe in receiuing the Lords
Supper in the morning, doth proue that that bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10126:36"/>
is aboliſhed, becauſe wee obſerue not the ſame cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance
of time. We keepe not indeede the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday
as the <hi>Thraskites,</hi> but we celebrate the Lords day;
the Sabbath being not aboliſhed, but altered from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday
to the Sonday, and that by order from Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
who immediately before his aſcenſion inſtructed his
Apoſtles in things belonging to the Kingdome of God,
<hi>Acts</hi> 1. 3. and the Sabbath I hope is one ſpeciall thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
to Gods kingdome; yea, our Sauiour taught vs
by his owne example to celebrate this day, appearing to
his Diſciples after his reſurrection, eſpecially vpon it, <hi>Iohn</hi>
20. 19. 26. Moreouer, the example of the Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
which celebrated this day, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 19. 26. ſhould
be a forcible motiue vnto vs to doe the like, for wee are
bound to follow them as they follow Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1.
and the occaſion of the alteration of the Sabbath was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary,
namely the reſurrection of our Lord, which
fel out not vpon the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Saturday, but vpon our Sonday,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 1. an occaſion which may very well deſerue the
honor of the day before that of Gods reſting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the works
of creation, although both the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are very renowned.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Obiection.</note> whereas they obiect that in <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. 13, 14,
15, 16. and <hi>Ezek</hi> 20. 12. where the Sabbath is tearmed a
ſigne. I anſwer, euery caeremonie is a ſigne, but euery ſigne
is not a caeremonie. The Sacraments are ſignes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11.
and yet not fading caeremonies.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, whereas they obiect that in <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 16. <hi>Let no
man iudge you in reſpect of Sabbaths:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Obiect.</note> and that in <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.
10, 11. <hi>Ye obſerue dayes and times, and moneths, and yeares,
I am in feare of you.</hi> I anſwer, by Sabbaths in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
are meant certaine caeremoniall dayes amongſt the
<hi>Iews;</hi> viz. their feaſt of Tabernacles, their new Moones, and
the like: for theſe are tearmed Sabbaths, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 23. 24.
and the Apoſtle doth ſufficiently expreſſe himſelfe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
ſuch dayes, and not the morall Sabbath, naming new
Moones, and other caeremoniall times. The like may be
anſwered vnto that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 5. one man eſteemeth one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10126:36"/>
day aboue another; another man eſteemeth euery day
alike, &amp;c. It is not meant that the Church made no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
in thoſe times between the Lords day and any other
day, as the Familiſts would peruert it; but that they which
were better informed then others, made no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
the ancient Caeremoniall dayes, which were now
aboliſhed, and other common dayes.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. Obiect.</note> whereas they alleadge that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. and <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. 23. as though our Sauiour had
defended the breach of the Sabbath, &amp; ſo by conſequence
had abrogated it. I anſwer, it is the ſcope of our Sauiour
in thoſe places to defend the lawfulneſſe of works of mercy
and works of neceſſitie, and not in any ſort to plead for the
abrogation of the Sabbath, much leſſe of the Lords day.</p>
               <p>Fiftly,<note place="margin">5. Obiect.</note> whereas they obiect that in <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 8. where our
Sauiour commands a manifeſt ſeruile worke to be done
vpon the Sabbath; namely, the carrying of a Bed. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
the carrying of the Bed in that place is not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
as a ſeruile worke, but to confirme the truth of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle
tending greatly to Gods glory: euen as our Sauiour
commanded to giue meat to the Damoſell whom he raiſed
from death, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 55. not ſo much for neceſſity, as for the
confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the truth of the Miracle wrought vpon her.</p>
               <p>Sixtly,<note place="margin">6. Obiect.</note> whereas they obiect that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 3. 9. we that
haue beleeued doe enter into reſt; whereby it might ſeeme
that the Sabbath of Chriſtians, or their reſt is meerely my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall.
I anſwer, that place of Scripture doth not treat of
the morall Sabbath as though that were myſticall, but of
our eternal reſt in heauen whereinto we enter at our death
by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Seauenthly,<note place="margin">7. Obiect.</note> whereas they obiect that in <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 13.
23. 33. where <hi>Cleophas</hi> and the other Diſciple went to
<hi>Emmaus,</hi> which was ſixtie ſurlongs from <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that
is, about ſeauen miles (a mile conſiſting of eight furlongs)
and returned againe the ſame day, which was vpon that
day which we call the Lords day, and therefore that they
made no ſuch ſcruple of working or trauelling vpon the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10126:37"/>
Lords day as we doe. I anſwer, it was not knowne to all
the Diſciples (this being the very day of Chriſt his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection)
that they ought to celebrate the firſt day of the
weeke; and therefore it was no maruell if they trauelled
vpon that day. The good women which made ſcruple to
annoint the body of Chriſt vpon the Sabbath, made no
ſcruple to come to doe it vpon the firſt day of the weeke,
becauſe as yet they were ignorant that they ought to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate
that day.</p>
               <p>Eightly,<note place="margin">8. Obiect.</note> whereas they obiect that the day which wee
obſerue is tearmed the firſt day of the weeke, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 1.
and therefore that it is a weeke day, not a Sabbath day. I
anſwer, this is a meere cauill. For it is tearmed the firſt
day of the weeke, not ſimply, but in reſpect of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi>
Saturday; in which regard alſo it is called the eight day
in diuers places. But when the Spirit in Scripture ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
poſitiuely and ſimply of it, hee tearmes it the Lords
day, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1. 10. which is indeede the moſt proper name
of it, although wee vſe a latitude of words in expreſſing
one and the ſame thing by diuers names.</p>
               <p>Ninthly,<note place="margin">9. Obiect.</note> whereas they obiect that they keepe euery day
a Sabbath, and therefore that they are vniuſtly taxed for
Sabbath-breakers; yea, that they come to the Church vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Lords day as well as others, and heare Sermons,
and receiue the Sacraments, &amp;c. that they hold the mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
of the fourth Commandement, and the like. I anſwer,
if to trade, to labour in their particular callings, and to
eſteeme euery day alike, be to keepe euery day a Sabbath,
then they keepe euery day a Sabbath; but what is this but
vnder colour of keeping euery day, to keepe no day at all
as it ought to bee kept. Secondly, we denie not but they
may come to the Church as well as others vpon the Lords
day, and heare the Word, and receiue the Sacrament; but
in the meane time how doe they demeane themſelues
when they haue heard? is it not famouſly knowne how
they meet together to cenſure the Miniſters, to contradict
the Doctrine, &amp;c. doe not hundreds in the Citie know this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:10126:37"/>
to be true, and was it not depoſed againſt them: againe
though they may receiue the Sacrament to keepe them
from trouble, yet what reuerent opinion haue they of the
Sacraments, eſpecially of Baptiſme, affirming that it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
conferres not confirmes grace to the heart of any: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares
in <hi>Ieſops</hi> booke, at page 61. Thirdly, they do meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
equiuocate when they ſay they hold the morality of the
fourth Commandement: for the morality of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
is that one day of ſeauen ſhould bee ſet apart
for Gods worſhip, and kept for conſcience ſake in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
to Gods Commandement: but this they are notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
knowne to denie that any ſuch day ſhould bee now
celebrated in conſcience of Gods Lawe: and therefore
they doe denie the morality of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the right ſenſe thereof.</p>
               <p>Tenthly,<note place="margin">10. Obiect.</note> whereas they obiect out of Maſter <hi>Tyndals</hi>
Workes, or ſome other bound vp with his, that the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
Fathers haue beene of their opinion concerning the
Sabbath. I anſwer, that is as true as the vaine boaſt of
Popiſh Champions which pretend that all the Fathers are
on their ſides.</p>
               <p>Indeed the Fathers and Doctors of the Church muſt be
read carefully and warily in this point concerning the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,
or elſe men may eaſily miſtake their meaning and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe
their iudgement. They ſpeake of diuers kindes of
Sabbaths: Firſt, of a Sabbath of the<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. liv. de ſpirit &amp; lit.</note> letter, whereby is
meant the Iewiſh or Traskite Sabbath. Secondly, of a
<note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt. lib. 13. confeſſion.</note> myſticall Sabbath, which is a reſting vpon God. Thirdly,
of a<note n="*" place="margin">Hier. in 56. Iſaia edit pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 1578. Dedicata Sab. bata, an other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition hath it: but I conceiue DELICATA is the truer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, quaſi Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bata ſumma iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunditatis &amp; dulcedinis.</note> delicate Sabbath, when a Chriſtian is made one
ſpirit with Chriſt, as one of the antients ſpeakes. Fourthly,
of a ſpirituall Sabbath, when we depart from inquity, and
become practiſers of ſanctification as<note n="h" place="margin">Cyrill Alexand. lib. 7 de adorat in ſpirit &amp; verit.</note> another of the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents
ſpeakes, if that worke by the cunning of ſome be not
wrongfully aſcribed vnto him. Fifthly, of an<note n="n" place="margin">Hier. in 58. Iſaiae.</note> eternall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
in heauen, which is an eternall reſt in that moſt bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
place. Sixthly, of a<note n="o" place="margin">Tertul. lib. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Iudaeos.</note> mortall Sabbath, which is a day
ſet apart by God himſelfe in the fourth Commandement
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10126:38"/>
for his owne ſeruice. Seuenthly, of an<note n="r" place="margin">Bern. Ser. 11. in Cantic.</note> idle Sabbath, when
men will reſt from the workes of their particular callings
vpon the Sabbath day, but will not imploy themſelues in
Gods Seruice: now theſe Ignoramuſ-ſes when they heare
that the Fathers ſpeake of a myſticall Sabbath, preſently
they conceiue as though the morrall Sabbath were meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
myſticall; and when they heare that the Farhers ſpeake
of an ildle Sabbath, they preſently cenſure the morall Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath
to be in the iudgement of the ancients an idle day: and
thus they peruert the iudgement of antiquity many times.
I ſpeake not this to iuſtifie all the Fathers in euery particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
ſentence of theirs concerning the Sabbath, <hi>quandoque
bonus dormitat Homerus,</hi> as<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. de arte Poet.</note> 
                  <hi>Horace</hi> ſaith of <hi>Homer: Et
Bernhardus non vidit omnia,</hi> as it is in the Prouerbe: the
Fathers haue had their Naeuos or failings in their writings
as a<note n="c" place="margin">Abrahamus Sculictus in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulla.</note> learned man hath affirmed: and ſo in like manner,
ſome of our moderne Writers haue giuen more power
to the Church to diſpoſe of the Sabbath, and to alter it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
concerning the day, ſo ſhee obſerue one day in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:
then I hope any Church vnder the Sunne, dare to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate
vnto her ſelfe vpon their affirmations, not being
ſufficiently aware how their meanings might bee abuſed
and peruerted by Familiſts and other Antiſabbatareans:
but what I ſpeake, I ſpeake it for the iuſt reproofe of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts
and ſuch like, which are glad if they can catch any
thing, if it be but in ſound onely, from the Writings of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
men, to patronize at the leaſt in ſhew their owne
hereticall and ſchiſmaticall opinions, like vnto ſpiders
ſucking poyſon from thoſe writings; from the which a
more iudicious Reader would deriue ſound edification and
inſtruction.</p>
               <p>Thus for Confutation concerning the Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:10126:38"/>
               <head>Hetheringtons opinion confuted concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the Bookes of Eſdras.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond thing which we propounded concerning
matter of Confutation, is touching the Bookes of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras:</hi>
the which bookes <hi>Hetherington</hi> holdeth (as hath
beene proued againſt him by witneſſes) to bee canonicall
Scripture, and that they ought ſo to be eſteemed: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
may appeare the pride and inſolency of this man, who
being altogether vnlearned (<hi>vt potè qui nullam linguam
nouit praeter ſuam maternam</hi>) yet will take vpon him in
oppoſition to the whole Church both reformed and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed,
to canonize new Scripture: in which particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
he ſheweth himſelfe to be worſe then the very Papiſts:
the<note n="c" place="margin">Bellar. lib. 1. de verbo dei.</note> Papiſts though they haue receiued ſome other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryphall Bookes into the Canon; yet they haue reiected,
or at the leaſt not receiued the Bookes of <hi>Eſdras:</hi> but let
him and his Proſelytes know <hi>tutiſſimum eſſe,</hi> that it is the
ſafeſt courſe as Saint<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. 2. de doct. Chriſtian c. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, to receiue onely
for Canonicall Scripture, ſuch bookes as all Catholike
Churches receiue. And indeede it concernes authority
to take this to heart; for if it were at euery priuate mans
choice what bookes he would receiue to bee Canonicall,
what would become of the true Chriſtian Faith, or what
ſwarmes of errors and corruption of faith would not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
inuade the Church as wee ſee in Popery, whilſt
they haue receiued pretended Apoſtolicall Traditions, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded
into the Canon diuers Apocryphall bookes, and
entertained the<note n="n" place="margin">Bellar. lib. 3. de eccleſ. c. 14.</note> ſentences of the Pope and the Court of
Rome as inertant truth, and haue<note n="o" place="margin">Trident concil. 1. decret. Seſſ. 4.</note> equalized traditions
to the Canonicall Scripture, what is become of the
Orthodoxe faith amongſt them? It is either farre to ſeeke,
or elſe miſerably corrupted.</p>
               <p>And the Reaſons to proue the bookes of <hi>Eſdras</hi> not to
be Canonicall Scripture againſt this Sectary, are theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10126:39"/>
Firſt, becauſe they were written at the firſt, not
in Hebrew, as the bookes of the Old Teſtament were but
in Latine: and<note n="c" place="margin">In prolog. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat. ad Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> is very confident in this, that
whatſoeuer Books of the old Teſtament were not written
in Hebrew,<note n="c" place="margin">Vide etiam praeſat. in lib. regum. Tom. 3.</note> they are not canonicall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe the Church in former times hath not
receiued them for canonicall; receiuing onely the 22 books
of the Old Teſtament as they were antiently diuided:
and what theſe 22 bookes were may bee gathered out of
<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 3. eccleſ. hiſt. cap. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> and<note n="g" place="margin">Lib. 1. contra Appion. gramat.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſephus:</hi> but eſpecially out of <hi>Hierom,</hi> who
doth more cleerely reiect the Apocryphall bookes in the
forenamed place then ſome other of the Fathers doe. I
will not inſiſt vpon further teſtimonies out of<note n="n" place="margin">Lib. de menſur &amp; p<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
out of<note n="o" place="margin">In Synopſi.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> out of<note n="p" place="margin">Catech. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyrill</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
out of<note n="q" place="margin">Lib 4, Orthod. fid. c. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Damaſcene</hi> and others: becauſe I haſten
to a concluſion? I know we are not any further bound to
agree to former Churches in iudgement, then ſo farre as
they agreed to the truth eſpecially in matters of Faith: but
yet to depart from the ancient Churches in that wherein
they are ſound and Orthodoxe, is horrible preſumption
and be wrayeth very much pride.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a learned man of our Church ſaith of all other
Apocryphall bookes, the bookes of <hi>Eſdras</hi> are worthy of
the leaſt credit being ſtuffed full of vaine fables,<note n="r" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Willet in his Synopſis.</note> fitter to
feede curious eares, then tending to edification.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, thoſe bookes are not to bee eſteemed Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall,
in the which there be errors, but in the bookes of
<hi>Eſdras</hi> there be errors, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there be errors in the third Books of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> I
referre the learned to the annotacions of <hi>Iunius</hi> vpon it;
and that there be errors in the fourth Booke, I might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
proue by inſtance. For firſt, in the fourth Chapter, the
Author ſaith that ſoules are kept in the wombe of the
earth. In the ſixth Chapter, there is a tayle of two great
fiſhes, <hi>Henoch,</hi> and <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> which no waters could
hold. In the fourteenth Chapter hee reporteth, that the
Bookes of Scripture being loſt in the Captiuity, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10126:39"/>
by him, and how hee had drunke of a cup of water
as fier in colour giuen by an Angell, and ſo ſpake 40 daies
together and ceaſed not; in the which ſpace, fiue Scribes
wrote from his mouth 204 Bookes; theſe and ſuch like
tales that Booke is full of, as our Learned Country man
ſpeaketh, whom I quoated before. I doe not denie but in
theſe bookes of <hi>Eſdras</hi> there may be many truths, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
the three laſt Chapters of the third booke, which are
almoſt a meere tranſcript out of the canonicall <hi>Eſra</hi> and
<hi>Nehemiah:</hi> but yet I muſt ſay of them, as Saint<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 15. de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. c. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
ſaith of them, and of all the reſt of the Apocrypha:
<hi>in his autem Apocryphis, etſi inuenitur aliqua veritas, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
propter multa falſa nulla eſt canonica authoritas,</hi> in theſe
Apocryphall bookes, although there be found ſome truth,
yet in reſpect of many falſe things found in them they haue
no canonicall authority.</p>
               <p>And thus I haue done with the ſecond thing propounded;
namely, the Conſutation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An exhortation to Chriſtian people remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
ſound in the Faith.</head>
               <p>HAuing diſpatched the two former branches concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
Diſcouery and Confutation, come wee now to
the third, which concernes matter of Exhortation, and to
beginne with Exhortation to the Chriſtian brethren,
which ſtill by the mercy of God remaine ſound in the
Faith.</p>
               <p>Good people, you haue heard in all the foregoing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
of falſe teachers, and alſo how many ſuch at theſe
dayes remaine amongſt vs, ſeducing many in their priuate
conuenticles: giue me leaue in the next place, by way of
introduction, to ſhew you the reaſons wherefore the Lord
ſuffereth ſuch in his Church, and then to propound ſome
preſeruatiues againſt ſeduction, which may ſerue for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
of Exhortation. For the firſt of theſe; The Lord ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
Seducers in his Church with long patience, and doth
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10126:40"/>
not preſently roote them out, for diuers reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the goodneſſe of truth might the more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,
who could know the benefit of light vnleſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
we were ſenſible of the darkeneſſe of the night, as
<note n="c" place="margin">Quis ſciret bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam eſſe lucem niſi noctis tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras ſentiremus. hom. 9. in c. 16. &amp; 17. numer.</note> Saint <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith; euen ſo who canne know the benefit
of health but by the ſmart of ſickneſſe, or the benefit of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
but by reſtraint or impriſonment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the word might bee the more deepely
ſought into. The myſtery of the Trinity had neuer beene
ſo exactly handled by many of the Fathers in<note n="c" place="margin">De Triait.</note> whole Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates
had not diuers damnable Heretickes ſprung vp to
oppoſe the ſame: wherein the Lord ſhewed his ſingular
wiſedome (as hee did alſo in the firſt Creation) bringing
light out of darkneſſe, truth out of error, good out of euill,
contraries out of contraries.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to trie the Gouernors of the Church, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
like vnto the Church of <hi>Pergamus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magiſtratus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat virum.</note> they will tolerate
ſuch as hold the doctrine of <hi>Balaam, Reu.</hi> 2. 12. or with the
Church of <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> ſuffer the woman <hi>Ieſabel</hi> that calleth
her ſelfe a propheteſſe to teach, and to ſeduce Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
<hi>Reu.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, he doth it for the puniſhment of ſuch as haue
itching eares and vnconſtant mindes, which are neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
with any true teachers, eſpeciall in publique, but
haue a luſting after the onyons and garlike of priuate er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,
preferring any thing done in a priuate Conuenticle
(though it be neuer ſo vnwholeſome) before that which is
done in the publike Congregation:<note place="margin">Nolunt doctores probos &amp; fidos, quid ergo reſtat? veniant adula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores. Caluin in Mich. c. 2. v. 11.</note> it is iuſt with God
to leaue ſuch curious perſons to bee ſeduced by falſe
Prophets to their owne eternall deſtruction, <hi>Micha</hi>
2. 11.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, God doth it that they which are approued may
be knowne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 19. a ſound Chriſtian is neuer bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
diſcerned, then when hee is compared with ſome
erroneous and hereticall perſon, hence it is that
Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith in one of his<note n="e" place="margin">Epiſt. 50.</note> Epiſtles, <hi>haereſis
enim &amp; ſcandala futura praedicta ſunt vt inter mimicos
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10126:40"/>
erudiamur ac ſic &amp; fides &amp; dilectio noſtra poſſit eſſe
probatior.</hi> Wee learne inſtruction amongſt Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
enemies, thereby our faith and loue are better
tryed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus for the Reaſons wherefore God ſuffreth Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes
in his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that you may be preſerued from Seducers on
euery ſide, which I hartily wiſh. Let mee commend
vnto you theſe Antidotes againſt ſeduction by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, labour to be well inſtructed in the grounds and
principles of true religion, how eaſily is an houſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
which hath no foundation: euen ſo how ſoone is a
man remoued from that truth wherein hee was neuer
grounded and rooted? for the which cauſe in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue
Church, as<note n="c" place="margin">Antequam da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur baptiſmus adultis, inſtitue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur in fidei rudimentis. Aug. lib. de fid. &amp; oper.</note> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, Baptiſme was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred
to no Heathen turning Chriſtian, but vnto ſuch
as were firſt inſtructed in points of Catechiſme: and this
indeede was an excellent meanes to preuent inconſtancie
and apoſtaſie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, receiue the truth in the loue of it; men are
hardly drawne from<note n="e" place="margin">Tu licet vſque ad Tanaim fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, vſque ſequc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur amor. propert. Eleg. lib. 2. ad Cyn<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. verſ. 1160</note> that they loue: <hi>Dauid</hi> loued the
Law better then Gold and Siluer; and hence it was that
hee could neuer be drawne from it by any Idolatrous
ſeducer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. There is no greater cauſe, why ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
become Apoſtates from the truth, then want of ſound
loue vnto it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, labour that your knowledge in Religion may
be experimentall: a man is hardly perſwaded by any art
againſt his owne experience: tell a man of meane vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
that the Crow is white, and the Snow blake,
yea vſe all the logicke you can to proue it, you ſhall neuer
perſwade him: and why? becauſe he knowes the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
by experience: euen ſo, if we knew by experience what
it were to deny our ſelues, and to depend vpon Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
for iuſtification, no Papiſt ſhould euer be able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
vs to truſt to humane merits: and if wee knew by
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:10126:41"/>
experience the infinite benefit of Gods Sabbath, no Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt
ſhould euer preuaile with vs to haue it in contempt:
<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> experience maketh men reſolute.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, beware of reading ſchiſmatical books,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrates</hi> was more reſolute in his old age to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der goe danger then the young men, becauſe he had experience. Plat. in Euthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</note> though
they be offred vnto you as a friendly gift; beware of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting
the company and conuenticles of ſeducers,
though you Be neuer ſo kindely inuited by falſe friends;
ſeeming friendly gifts tending to ſeduction, are like the
<hi>Troian</hi> horſe, which was pretended to be the<note n="c" place="margin">Pars ſtupet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nupta adnum exitiale miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uae. Virgil AE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nead. lib. 2.</note> gift of
<hi>Minerua,</hi> but it proued The deſtruction of <hi>Troy.</hi> In the
<hi>Romiſh</hi> Church the common people are not permitted to
meddle with our bookes. I would they were not in this
particular more prouident for Antichriſt, then we are for
Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, be practicall in Religion: be doers of the will of
God, and then ye ſhall know of the doctrine, whether it
be of God, or whether the teacher ſpeakes of himſelfe, as
our Sauiour in effect ſpeaketh, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7. 16. if it be well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued
what kinde of Profeſſors they be ordinarily which
fall of from the Church to ſects and ſchiſmes. I doe not
doubt but it will eaſily appeare, that for the moſt part
they are ſuch, as had a forme of godlineſſe, but denied the
power, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of the hypocrites of his time,
2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> whereupon <hi>Theophilact</hi> ſaith moſt truely in
his Annotations vpon <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. whoſoeuer ſhall build
his ſoule vpon the practiſe of Chriſts Commandements, no
temptations ſhall euer be able to caſt him downe.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, when you haue any ſcruple in your conſciences,
repaire not to ſeducers for reſolution, but according to
Gods ordinance, aske the Prieſts concerning the Law,
<hi>Agg.</hi> 2. 11. and ſeeke the Law at their mouthes, <hi>Malach.</hi>
2. 7. goe to your faithfull Miniſters, and let them reſolue
you; and if you be tempted by ſeducers, acquaint them
with your temptations, that they may ſtrengthen you.
Conſider what I ſay, and the Lord giue you vnderſtanding
in all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:10126:41"/>
               <head>An exhortation for Hetherington and all other
Sect-masters about the Citie of London
or elſe-where.</head>
               <p>YOu which haue beene the meanes to ſeduce many ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſoules from the truth, I beſeech you, if you be not
come to that height of wickedneſſe, as to ſit downe in the
chaire of ſcorners;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> or as the Septuagints render it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
in the chaire of peſtilence: let my counſell
be auaileable with you, and break of your vngodly courſe
of ſeducing Gods ſeruants. I know you rage againſt mee
for going about to reclaime you, and for endeauouring to
preſerue my flocke from your ſeducements: but may it
not iuſtly be ſaid of you in this reſpect, as<note n="c" place="margin">Serm. 5. de lapſis.</note> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>
ſaith of ſome in his time; <hi>Sacerdotibus ſacrilegus iraſc<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
atque ò tuam nimiam furioſè dimentiam, iraſceris ei
qui abs te auertere iram dei nititur, ei minaris, qui pro te
domini miſericordia<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> deprecatur: qui vulnus tuum ſentit,
quod ipſe non ſentis.</hi> O Furious man, is not this too much
madneſſe in thee; thou art angry with him which endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth
to auert Gods wrath from thee; thou threatneſt
him which imploreth mercy for thee at the hands of God,
which feeles thy wound which thou thy ſelfe doſt not
feele. But to paſſe by your furie with compaſſion, I will
endeauour to cure you of your phrenſie, and that two
wayes. Firſt, by ſhewing you the cauſes of your diſeaſe as
a neceſſary preface: and ſecondly by applying ſome cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziues
by way of exhortation.</p>
               <p>And the cauſes of your diſeaſes are diuers. Firſt, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
of the true ſenſe of Scripture, according to that in
<hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 29. <hi>Doe yee not therefore erre, not knowing the
Scriptures:</hi> whereupon<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in praefat in Epiſt. ad rom. in edit Co<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>elin.</note> Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaith, much
hereſie hath firſt ſprung from ignorance of Scripture: you
thinke, as appeares by your practice, that you are the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10126:42"/>
knowers of Gods minde in his word; but alas your
owne hearts doe deceiue you: many of you are ignorant
of the originall tongues wherein the Scriptures were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
and ſo doe want one eſpeciall helpe for the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
of them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you are knowne to deſpiſe all Orthodox wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
whoſe Commentaries might helpe you. And thirdly,
that you are not guided by the ſpirit of truth, appeares by
your groſſe errors peeuiſhly maintained by you: the which
three may well conuince you of ignorance.</p>
               <p>2. The ſecond cauſe of your diſeaſe is pride: you mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
your owne wiſedome; ſome of you maintaine that
you cannot erre in giuing deliberate ſentence in points of
Diuinite; you diſable the Miniſters of the Church, as
though they knew nothing in compariſon of you; and this
knowledge of yours, or rather this proud conceit of your
owne ſuppoſed knowledge cauſeth you to erre, according
to that of<note n="c" place="margin">Mater omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um hareticorum ſuperbia. Aug. de Geneſ. contra Manich.</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> pride is the mother which
breedeth and bringeth forth the whole brood of Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.
Wherefore lay downe your owne vaine conceits of
your pretended skill, and deſire of God that you may ſee
your owne nothing-neſſe and vnabilitie, that ſo you may
be healed: thinke it not an honour to be the head of an
erronious and factious company, or to be reuerenced by
them, as the<note n="e" place="margin">Pierius in hic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyph.</note> 
                  <hi>Athenians</hi> in former times worſhipped the
Woolfe: deſpiſe that honour which comes not of God:
thinke it a diſgrace to be commended by euill men.</p>
               <p>3. The third cauſe of your diſeaſe is couetouſneſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to that which is ſpoken of Sectaries in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.
18. <hi>they that are ſuch ſerue not our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, but
their owne belly.</hi> How many time-ſeruers be there which
will ſooth great men in their errors, and ſeeme to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
the errors of the time for their owne aduantage? and
how many wauering tradeſmen which will readily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
that faction whereby they may moſt aduance their
owne gaine: which gaue occaſion in like manner to<note n="n" place="margin">Haereticus eſt vt mea reſert o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinio, qui alicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius temporalis commodi &amp; max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè gloriae prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatuſque ſui gratia falſas ac nouas opiniones vel gignit vel ſequitur. Aug. li. de vtilit. cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend.</note> Saint
<hi>Augustine</hi> in his time to deſcribe an Haereticke by his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10126:42"/>
couetouſneſſe and vaine-glory, as you haue it in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.
Wherefore if euer you meane to be cured of your
factiouſneſſe, deſpiſe the baſe gaine of it: doe not thinke it
ſo excellent a matter to get by your ſuffrings, going poore
into the priſon, but comming rich out: account it not a
priuiledge to haue your proſelytes to boaſt vp and
downe, that you ſhall want neither Gold nor Siluer:
remember that of <hi>Salomon, the treaſures of wickedneſſe
profit nothing, Pro.</hi> 10. 2. and that of our Sauiour in <hi>Mat.</hi>
16. 26. <hi>What is a man profited if hee ſhould gaine the whole
world, and looſe his owne ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus hauing ſhewed you the maine cauſes of your
diſeaſe, I come now to giue or to apply vnto you ſome
coraziues, to eat out the dead fleſh of error or Haereſie:
Haereſie being one of the fruits of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 20. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
therefore and lay to heart, what dreadful iudgements
haue befallen your predeceſſors for their factious carriage
in the Church of God: remember what befell vnto <hi>Theu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,
Acts</hi> 5. 36, 37. who boaſted himſelfe to be ſome body,
as you alſo doe, <hi>to whom a number of men about</hi> 400. <hi>ioyned
themſelues, who was ſlaine, and all as many as obeyed him
were ſcattered abroad and brought to nought:</hi> and after
this man <hi>roſe vp Iudas of Galile in the dayes of taxing, and
drew away much people after him, he alſo periſhed, and all as
many as obeyed him, were diſperſed.</hi> Of the which two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers
alſo<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 18 c. 1. &amp;</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſephus</hi> makes mention in his<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 20. c. 2.</note> Antiquities.
Secondly, remember what befell vnto <hi>Elymas</hi> for going
about to turne away the Deputie from the faith, how hee
was immediately ſmitten with blindneſſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 11. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
what befell vnto <hi>Arius,</hi> whoſe damnable Haereſie
for a time much preuailed, how he died in a Iakes, where
he voided his very bowels with his excrements, as<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 1. Eccleſ. hiſt c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi>
recordeth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, remember what befell vnto <hi>Anastaſius</hi> an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a great defender of <hi>Eutichian</hi> Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes,
how he was found dead, being ſmitten as it was
commonly thought with a thunderbolt from heauen, as
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:10126:43"/>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Melanct lib. 3. Chron.</note> 
                  <hi>Philip Melancton</hi> hath it in his Chronicle. Fourthly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
what befell <hi>Nestorius,</hi> another ringleader of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
in the Church of God, how before his death his
tongue (which hee had abuſed in broaching errors) was
conſumed with wormes, as<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. 14. c. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus Callistus</hi> hath
left it vpon record. Fiftly, remember what befell the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
of <hi>Antioch,</hi> which was a great nouriſher of faction, as
<hi>Amsterdam</hi> is at this day, how it was ſhaken with an
earthquake a whole yeere together, and afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
with fire from heauen, as<note n="o" place="margin">Lib. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Paulus Diaconus</hi> ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth
of it: and as in like manner <hi>Socrates</hi> ſeemeth to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
in the<note n="r" place="margin">Lib 4. c. 10.</note> tripartite Hiſtorie.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, remember what befell the Papiſts here in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
not<note n="s" place="margin">Anno. 1623. Octob. 26. being Sonday.</note> long ſince, how that when they were met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
in an houſe in Blacke-friers, in an vpper roome to
heare a<note n="t" place="margin">The Sermon of one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Drurie a Prieſt and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite.</note> Popiſh Sermon, the roome wherein they were,
fell, and ſome other parts of the houſe, and ſodainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
a<note n="u" place="margin">Aboue 90. perſons.</note> multitude of them, and maimed others, which
hardly eſcaped with their liues. I will not inſiſt vpon more
examples of <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus,</hi> of <hi>Manes,</hi> of <hi>Montanus,</hi>
and other Haeretickes who are reported alſo to haue come
to fearefull ends. Theſe which haue beene named may be
ſufficient, to forewarne any which haue any ſparke of
grace remaining in them, to beware of faction: and a
thouſand more will not be ſufficient to them which are
hardned in their hearts. O thinke with your ſelues all yee
which miſleade others, that the like iudgements may befal
you. God is a mighty God, and of infinite wiſedome; he
is able to diſcerne your meanings, &amp; what you hold, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
all your equiuocations, ſubtile diſtinctions,
cunning euaſions, and fearefull abiurations which you vſe,
thereby to couer your errors from the ſight of authority:
yea, he is able to reach you with his iudgements whether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
you flye. Or ſuppoſe the Lord inflict not vpon you
corporall puniſhment in this world, yet know for certaine,
<hi>Non maior eſt pana quam peccare:</hi> he puniſheth you moſt
ſeuerely in this, in that hee deliuers you vp to a blinded
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:10126:43"/>
minde; yea, vnleſſe you repent, you haue iuſt cauſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
to haue part with the beaſt and the falſe Prophet in
hell torments, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19. 20. which I pray God to auert
from you. Thus I haue endeauoured as a friend (although
you eſteeme me an enemie, becauſe I tell you the truth)
to turne you from your errors: if my paines ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile
with you, I ſhall reioyce with the Angels of God for
your conuerſion; I ſhall for the time to come eſteeme you
deere brethren; <hi>Et gaudebo ſanè me tot habere fratres.</hi> I
will not once mention your calumnies and reproaches
wherewith you haue loaded me for taking part with Gods
truth, I pray God forgiue you: it is a rule in Phyloſophie,
<hi>quicquid recipitur, recipitur ad modum recipientis:</hi> which
I will engliſh thus; good counſell is as it is taken by them
to whom it is giuen: but take not that with the left hand
which I offer with the right. I deſire to pull you out of
the fire, to preſerue you from falling into the pit of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
perdition; to plucke you out of the iawes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring
Lyon: let it not be ſaid of me (as<note n="c" place="margin">In panulo, Act. 3. ſcen. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith
of them, <hi>Lupo agnam eripere poſtulant, nugas agunt</hi>) that
I looſe my labour; that I would haue cured you, but vee
would not be cured; that I would haue ſaued you Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially,
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 16. but yee would not be ſaued: but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
I preuaile not with you, becauſe you are ſetled vpon
your Lees, yet I hope to perſwade ſome that formerly haue
beene ſeduced by you, to be more iealous of your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
for the time to come, and not to receiue euery point
which you erroniouſly hold, as an euerlaſting Goſpell.
And ſay I ſhould perſwade neither you nor them, but you
will ſtill remaine Wolues in the Church of God, and they
ſtray ſheepe wandering in the deſolate vallies, as a prey rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
to be deuoured by you: then I muſt needs tel you, both
you and your ſpightfull proſelytes (ſpightfull I meane to
the Church of Chriſt) that if you delight to ſwim together
in the deluge of fundamentall error, you ſhall alſo, <hi>volen
tes nolentes,</hi> ſwim together in the deluge of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
and ſo that ſhall be verified of you:<note n="d" place="margin">Ouid. lib. 1. Metamor.</note> 
                  <hi>Nat Lupus
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10126:44"/>
inter oues, fuluos vehit vnda Leones.</hi> But as for me, I will
ſay with the Euangelicall Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> c. 49. 4. <hi>ſurely my
iudgement is with the Lord, and my worke with my God.</hi>
Now O God almightie grant, that what hath beene deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
at this time, may worke effectually for thy glory, for
the conuerſion or for the conuiction of the enemies of
thine eternall truth, and for the confirmation of vs thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
and that for thy bleſſed Sonne his ſake Ieſus Chriſt
the iuſt, to whom with thee O Father, and the holy Ghoſt,
three perſons moſt glorious, but one only wiſe God, be
aſcribed as is moſt due, all the honour, praiſe,
and glory now, henceforth, and for
euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 16. ſeuen for ſeuenth. page. 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 15. in
homini for in homine. p. 24 puniſceant for permiſceant p. 24. melius for mellis. p.
50. perſcutione for perſecu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ione. p. 66. tayle for tale.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10126:44"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
